<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<book>
Turkey,
Egypt,
and Syria
2020. Syracuse University Press.
All rights reserved. May not be reproduced in any form without permission from the publisher, except fair uses permitted under U.S. or applicable copyright law.
A Travelogue
Compiled by
Maulānā Shiblī Nu‘mānī
Entitled
Shams al-‘Ulamā’ [Sun of the Scholars]
Professor of Arabic at the Madrasat al-‘Ulūm, Aligarh
Fellow of the University of Allahabad
Printed at the Mufīd-i ‘Ām Press in Agrah
First Printing (1,000 copies)
EBSCO Publishing: eBook Collection (EBSCOhost) printed on 2/20/2026 7:32:21 PM UTC via UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH 1942825; Shibli Numani; Turkey, Egypt,
and Syria : A Travelogue Account:ehost.

Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
A Travelogue
In which, in addition to the small, interesting incidents that have arisen
in the course of the narrative, the following circumstances related to
Constantinople, Beirut, Jerusalem, Cairo, and so on, have been written
in detail—that is, general circumstances of the city, sights worth visit-
ing, famous buildings, the administration of the Department of Educa-
tion, academies and madrasas, boarding houses and students, women’s
education, writers and their writings, libraries, newspapers and journals,
encounters with famous pāshās and people of achievement, and the mor-
als and habits of the Turks and Arabs. In the end, there is a very brief
lexicon of the newly fashioned terms that have come into use in Egypt and
Syria today, without knowledge of which, people cannot take advantage of
Arabic newspapers.
Compiled by Shiblī Nu‘mānī
3

4 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
List of Subjects
SubjectPage SubjectPage
The Intention to Travel and
Beginning of the Journey
16 Types of Lodging in
Constantinople
34
From Bombay 17–18 The Companionship of
Shaikh ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ and His
Circumstances
35
Strange and Wondrous
Animals
21 Meeting Shaikh ‘Ali Zabyān
by Means of a Writing
35
Port Said 23 Arrangements for Food 36
A Superficial Visit to Beirut 25 Qaṣīdah-e Safariyah 36
Change in the Condition of
the Journey from Port Said
25 A Summary History of
Constantinople and Brief
Circumstances Thereof
41
The Indifference of Arabs by
Reason of an Iranian Cap
26 The Present Condition of
Constantinople
42
Cyprus 27 Fineness of Location and
Scenery
42
Izmīr, meaning Smyrna 29

Turkey, Egypt, and Syria 5
List of Subjects
SubjectPage SubjectPage
Dress and Fashion 46 Classical Education and
Classical Madrasas
69
Courts 47 The Intellectual-Scientific
Condition of the Turks
71
The State of Education 48 Newspapers and Journals 75
Modern Education and Its
Different Levels
49 More Caution Than
Moderation [Calls For] in the
Printing of Books
76
The Progress of Education in
the Age of the Present Sulṭān
and the Annual Expense of
Education
50 Print Shops 78
The Invitation of Students by
the Sulṭān
50 Libraries 79
Arrangements for the
Education of the Arab People
Especially
51 Zawāyā, Meaning Charitable
Traveler Lodges for Every
Country and Every Nation
86
Major Colleges and Schools 52 Congregational Mosques 87
The System of Boarding 54 Places Worth Seeing 89
The Dress of Students 56 Tars-khānah, Meaning Where
Official Ships Are Built
89
Lack in the Progress in
Education
58 Museum 92
The Military College 59 Places to Visit 93
The College of the Sulṭān 65 Muḥarram 94
The Mulkiyah College 68 Salāmlaq, Meaning the Great
SulṭāN’s Coming for Friday
NamāZ and the Armies’
Passing by for Inspection
95

6 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
List of Subjects
SubjectPage SubjectPage
Eid Procession 100 Societies and Newspapers 133
Mas˙navī-i ‘Īdiyah 100 Meeting Scholars and People
of Achievement
135
Turkish Morals, Habits, and
Style of Social Life
104 Departure from Beirut 138
The Education, Training,
Fashion, and Dress of Women
110 Bait al-Muqaddas [Jerusalem] 140
Hindustanis of
Constantinople
112 Masjid-i Aqṣā [The Aqsa
Mosque]
141
Dear Friends in
Constantinople
113 Qammāmah [The Church of
the Holy Sepulchre]
143
Meeting Ghazi ‘Us˙mān Pāshā 115 Meeting Scholars and
Learned Men and Some
Other Details
144
The Author’s Receiving
the Tamghah-I MajīDiyah
[MajīDiyah Medal] and a
Copy of the Tamghah and
the SulṭāN’s Decree
117 Departure from Bait
al-Muqaddas
146
Departure from
Constantinople
120 Cairo 148
An Unpleasant Event on
the Ship
121 The Educational State of Miṣr
[Egypt]
149
Beirut 123 The Number of Schools and
College and Their Expenses
150
The Intellectual-Scientific
Progress of Beirut
124 Dār al- ‘Ulūm 153
The University of Beirut 128

Turkey, Egypt, and Syria 7
SubjectPage SubjectPage
Law College 157 Burial Sites 176
Madrasa of Translation 158 Printing Houses and
Newspapers
177
Medical College 159 Theaters 179
Engineering College and
Madrasa of Industry and
General Madrasas
160 Clubs and Societies 180
People Receiving Education
in Europe
162 The Birthday of the Prophet
(ṣla‘m)
181
Jāmi‘-e Azhar [The Azhar
(Congregational) Mosque]
164 People of Achievement and
Writers
183
Official Library 168 The End of the Journey and
the Beneficent Morals of the
Arabs
187
Ancient Monuments 172 The Arabic Language of the
Present
191
List of Subjects
Note: On line 3 on page 230 [in the Urdu original], the word ḥawāyaj should be read instead as
awā‘ī, and this word should be counted among the words in the alif [a] section.


Preface
In the Name of God, the Compassionate, the Merciful
With Praise and Prayers1
Although we did not reach the land of roses in the season of roses
We did not let the spectacle of autumn fall from our hand.2
The journey that I made to Constantinople, and so on, in auspicious Ram-
z¨ān, 1309 Hijrī / [March/April] 1892 was purely a student’s journey, and
because it was neither an extraordinary affair, nor was there much rare-
ness in the happenings of the journey, I had absolutely no intention of
writing a travelogue. However, after I returned from there, the elders and
friends whom I had occasion to meet all demanded a travelogue. I thought
that since the custom of travel and journey stopped in our community
some time ago, and for this reason absolutely no acquaintance with the
true circumstances of the Islamic regions is acquired, this demand by the
people was not out of place. I was reminded of my own situation when,
before the journey, any time I met a traveler from Constantinople, and so
on, I would spend hours asking about the circumstances of that place. [3]
These were the reasons that persuaded me to give order to these scat-
tered pages. Otherwise, to record the circumstances of such a hasty and
ordinary journey, and to give it the name safarnāmah or kitāb al-riḥlat,
3
would not have been devoid of small wit. The kind of information that is
necessary and required in a safarnāmah, that is, the general circumstances
of the region, the method of administration, the principles of the court,
the particularities of business and commerce, and sketches of buildings;
not even one of these is found in this safarnāmah. Of course, there are
9

10 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
a substantial number of incidents related to social life and intellectual-scientific
circumstances, although they too are not as detailed as they
should be. In sum, whoever desires to see the Safarnāmah as a safarnāmah
will not be able to derive full pleasure from this book. Still, this potluck of
whatever was at hand can be presented at the table setting of people who
take pleasure in even the ordinary events of Islamic regions, for mā lā
yudrak kulluh lā yutrak kulluh.
4
Although I have not discussed the civilizational and regional cir-
cumstances of the Turks in this book, nor was a discussion of this kind
appropriate with respect to my position and status, the degree of cultural
refinement and propriety of the Turks that will be established in the hearts
of readers will be different from that which is expressed by the general
literature of Europe.
The thoughts against Muslims that Europe formed in some age in
the past were, for a time, expressed openly in such a way that the hue of
religious prejudice was clear to see, and at that time this was an excellent
means of general acceptance. But when the [4] power of religion declined
in Europe, and religious anthems became entirely ineffectual, that pol-
icy took a turn. Now it was not thought to be so beneficial to write such
clearly prejudiced words about Muslims. Instead, the learned, scholarly
practice was adopted that the flaws of Islamic governments, Islamic na-
tions, and Islamic society be laid bare in historical ornament, and these
have become so absorbed in the literature by means of common writ-
ings, stories, novels, and proverbs that they cannot be separated even by
a chemical solution.
Although this practice is employed with all Islamic nations, at this
time our discussion lies with the Turks in particular. Not having contemp-
tuous thoughts about Turks after reading European literature is precisely
like not feeling drowsy after taking a soporific drug.
The circle of scholars in Europe is quite extensive, and for this reason
there are people of every degree and class among them: prejudiced and
good hearted, superficial and discerning. But in discussion of the Turks,
this difference of degrees collapses entirely, and the same sound issues
from every instrument.

Preface 11
For example, the straightforward and honest account of the truest of
true European writers of today is that, in mentioning the Turkish govern-
ment, he writes entirely straightforwardly of the heaviness of debt, the
insufficiency of industry and technology, the absence of the expanse of
education in the provincial districts, the dependency on Europe for weap-
ons and armaments—all of this. But he so avoids mentioning the reforms
that have taken place of late that it is as if reform does not exist at all. The
administration of the treasury, the establishment of agricultural banks in
all the provincial districts, [5] the progression of the number of rushdiyah
schools from 96 to 405, the establishment of many large and great colleges,
the extensiveness of the railway, the arrangements for discharging debt,
the development of military power—he does not write about these events,*
not even by mistake.5
An extremely easy method of proving a nation or a person praisewor-
thy or contemptable is to paint a one-sided picture of its circumstances
and happenings, and the just truth of the matter is that Europe has used
this deceptive method more than all other nations in the world.
No doubt, there are also beneficent people in Europe who have noth-
ing to do with prejudice, but even their lack of prejudice is ineffective when
confronted with the kind of thoughts among which they have been raised
since childhood, the sources of information all around them, and the
voices that enter their ears from all directions. One gentleman, who is an
extremely unprejudiced and learned person and whom I have the honor
of serving, returned from a journey to Constantinople and Egypt, and I
asked in the course of conversation, “Did you also visit the Azhar Congre-
gational Mosque in Cairo?”6 He said, “I was very keen to visit it, but my
guide said that Christians were not permitted to go there;” although this
fact is purely erroneous. [6] I myself resided in the Azhar Congregational
*
A separate book has been written and published in Constantinople detailing the
intellectual-scientific and practical developments that have taken place in the time of the
present sulṭān, and the tract by Rāsim Bey Āfandī discussing naval progress in particular
has been published, the name of which is Daur-i taraqqī [The Age of Progress].

12 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Mosque for more than one month, and my Christian friends used to come
to meet me right in the masjid without any trouble. But because in Europe
the prejudice and narrow-mindedness of Muslims is very nearly axiomatic
knowledge, how could that ṣāḥib have had any hesitation in believing the
words of his guide?
To crown all, if anyone says or writes something that deviates from
the common thoroughfare, his voice is thought to be the voice of a par-
rot in the drum chamber of Europe. An English princess, having lived in
Constantinople for fifteen or sixteen years, wrote a book by the name of
The Twelve-Year Governance of ‘Abd al-Ḥamīd the Second.
7 Although to be
taken as credible—the intellectual capability of the authoress, the experi-
ence of fifteen or sixteen years, the authentic means of discovering infor-
mation—all the attendant requisites were present; still, because it was not
of one voice with Europe in speaking of the faults of the Turks, it was not
able to obtain the status of reliability and trustworthiness. We have heard
educated people say of it, “It would be no wonder if the Turks themselves
wrote the book under the name of an assumed author, or if favors from
the sulṭān compelled the British princess to write such a book!!” But if
the same book had been about the faults of the Turks, then (according to
these people) every letter of it would have been absolute and certain. Even
the essays that Professor Vámbéry has written drawing from his schol-
arly investigations into the cultural refinement and propriety of the Turks
remained ineffectual for the very reason that the aforementioned professor
had acknowledged the present intellectual-scientific progress of the Turks.8
Although this is the state of the common literature of Europe con-
cerning the Turks, with respect to the occasion, we should [7] mention in
particular the travelogues of Turkey, for it is from these very travelogues
that the resources of European historical writings have also largely been
taken. Although the travelogue is an interesting part of the historical tra-
dition, it is as replete with erroneous suppositions as it is interesting.
A major error that commonly befalls the writers of travelogues is
establishing generalizations from particulars. Human beings establish a
general view of an entire nation from the character, habits, and ideas of
the people whom they encounter on a journey, even though it is possible

Preface 13
that these matters are exclusive to those few people alone. Similarly, they
desire to derive a general conclusion from every occurrence, and neither
desire to spend time in search of the specific causes of each occurrence nor
have occasion to do so.
One major cause of error is that the person who travels to some coun-
try already has friendly or opposing ideas about it. After arriving there,
whatever he sees and hears at first is purely superficial, and because such
cursory familiarity is not sufficient for the derivation of conclusions, and
he cannot wait long to form conclusions, he therefore interposes conjec-
tures with every incident. While making such conjectures, the positive or
negative notion that already existed in his heart continues to act in silence
and the person is completely unaware. Although erroneous supposition
of this kind is connected with all the nations of the world, the people of
Europe enjoy special superiority in it, the reason for which is that no other
nation is [8] as impatient to derive conclusions as the Europeans. It is the
effect of this that when a common European traveler or politician happens
to turn up in Hindustan, on the basis of the experience of just a week or
two, he publishes major articles in European newspapers and magazines
claiming that it is as if all the secrets of the society and civilization of Hin-
dustan have been revealed to him.
Another major reason is that because the traveler is extremely eager
to discover information, he desires to acquire some resource or means of
information from every person he encounters. In this generalizing, he
does not care to discern if the person is trustworthy or untrustworthy,
enlightened or prejudiced, or someone with an eye for finer points or who
only sees the apparent, and even if he does desire to do so, he cannot do
so successfully. Europeans are even more incautious in this regard. Most
European tourists who travel to Constantinople typically have occasion to
stay in the hotels of Bayoghlī [Beyoğlu] and Ghalatah [Galata].9 Wherever
they want to go, a gāyad ˙ (guide) is with them who not only takes them on
a tour of the buildings and places, but also answers all the questions that
they ask from time to time as needed.10 These guides are generally Chris-
tian, and their rate is a rupee or two per day. Everyone can estimate for
oneself what kind of information these guides can have.

14 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Fāṭimah Khānam* has written in the preface of her book, “When
the esteemed European women [9] whom I had occasion to meet would
recount something relating to Turkish women as fact, I used to suspect
that they were discussing some other nation or they were stories in the
style of a novel.” Fatimah Khānam has also given the opinion that, “It is
not the fault of these poor people. They are compelled to believe whatever
guides say to tourists.” A guide also deceived our friend, who was deprived
of a visit to the Azhar Congregational Mosque.
In sum, it was inevitable that my travelogue would be different from
European writings and travelogues, although it would not have been befit-
ting to go into such excessive detail in describing the reasons for this dif-
ference that it became its own separate subject or section.
It is not at all necessary to express here the impression that the jour-
ney to Turkey has left on my heart. This can be learned by reading this
safarnāmah. Of course, it is necessary to say at the very least that if the
status of the sultanate is set aside, then the condition of Muslims there,
too, is not worthy of much joy or satisfaction. Rather, one should say that
in a great many matters, it is very close to that of Hindustani Muslims.
They have nothing to do with industry. They have very little share in com-
mercial trade. Even the ordinary shopkeepers are Jewish or Christian.
The old education is extremely defective [10] and continues to become
more and more so. The complaint concerning new education that is made
here is also made there. There is still enmity between the old culture and
the new culture, and no composite temperament has been produced by
mixing the two. Those of the old way of thinking are still unaware of the
*
This is an extremely esteemed and educated lady who, in addition to Arabic, Per-
sian, and Turkish (which is her mother tongue), knows French extremely well. In order
to reform the kind of erroneous information about Turkish women that Europe pos-
sesses (see page 9) [8–9] she has written a book in the form of novel whose name is Nisā’
al-Muslimīn [The Muslim Women]. This book has been translated into Arabic, and, hav-
ing been presented at the American exhibition, has been translated into English under
the care of that place. [The 1901–2 edition adds, “It has also been translated into Urdu,
and has been published at the Muhammadan Press at Aligarh.”] [Fāṭimah Khānam, Nisā’
al-muslimīn, trans. Sa‘īd Aḥmad (Aligarh: Muhammadan Press, n.d.)]

Preface 15
pace of the times. Those of the new taste do not do as much as they say.
Instead of courage, dignity, passion, resolve, and fortitude, something like
despondency has spread over the entire nation (predominantly). People
are content with whatever circumstance they find themselves in. The pres-
ent situation is, la‘allallāha yuḥdis˙u ba‘da żālika amran.
11
It Ended Well

The Intention to Travel
and Beginning of the Journey
The Reason for the Intention to Travel. At the time when the idea for the
Heroes of Islam1 occurred to me, the thought also occurred to me that the
historical material that existed in our country could not in any way suffice
for this purpose. It was this thought that initially produced the motiva-
tion for this journey in my heart because I was certain that such a series of
compositions could surely be prepared from the balance of Islamic writ-
ings that remains in Egypt and Turkey.
Although this resolution had already become firm, for various rea-
sons there continued to be a delay. So much so that for obvious reasons I
became somewhat hopeless, and the resolution remained nothing more
than a feeble idea. Last year, by a strange coincidence, this intention was
set in motion, and, with that motion, was completed. I was often ill last
year. So much so that, having grown weary of the treatments, I intended to
have a change of climate. Accordingly, I wrote numerous letters to friends
in Almora and Kashmir to arrange for a house, and so on. Meanwhile, I
learned that Mr. Arnold, who is professor of philosophy at the academy
and my ustād (I have learned French from him), was planning to go to
Europe in the coming days.2 At once the thought occurred to me that the
journey to Egypt and Turkey, the change of climate, the company of Mr.
Arnold—all these things had happened to come together; this moment
should be considered an extremely great blessing. [2] Thus, right then I
went to see the aforementioned gentleman to say, “I will go with you.” He
expressed extreme happiness and said, “As far as possible, I shall give you
sufficient assistance in the necessary tasks of the journey.”
16

The Beginning of the Journey 17
At that time, only three or four days remained before the departure of
the ship. When friends and dear ones heard, they were utterly astonished,
and most tried to make me understand, “Such a great journey with such
haste and lack of means; what kind of wisdom is this?” I said:
har chih bādābād man kashtī dar āb andākhtam.
3
Summer vacation at the college is typically three months long. As
per my period of employment, I was entitled to privileged leave of three
months. Thus, putting both together, I had six months’ leave, and on April
26, 1892, I left Aligarh. Mr. Arnold had departed for Jhansi a day or two
before to meet with a friend of his. We met at Jhansi station, and the entire
trip was spent in great pleasure and enjoyment. Mr. Arnold had informed
Hājī Raḥmatullāh bin Da’ūd, who is an esteemed and enlightened mer-
chant in Bombay, of his arrival by a means of a letter, in which my company
was also mentioned. Because, as it happened, our prior arrangements had
changed to some extent, we arrived at Bombay two days after the sched-
uled date. Mr. Arnold took his and my things to the Western hotel.4 I was
strolling around the market when I encountered a boy. I asked him, “Do
you know Ḥājī Raḥmatullāh?” He asked, “Aren’t you Maulawī Shiblī?”5 I
was amazed by this intuitive perception of his, which was nothing short of
revelation. He said, “We have been wondering about you for two days,” and
said, “Please, come with me. Ḥājī ṣāḥib is expecting you.” [3] Ḥājī ṣāḥib
called Mr. Arnold, too, from the hotel, and we both stayed in his garden.
Our ship was to depart on the day after we arrived at Bombay. Thus,
we spent all our time making the necessary preparations for the journey
and were not able to tour the Islamic madrasas and societies that are in
Bombay. We bought our ticket through the Cook Company.6 The rate of
a second-class ticket from Bombay to Port Said on the ship on which we
were going was 210 rupees. I made the terrible mistake of not buying a
return ticket, the result of which was that I was compelled to pay twenty-
one pounds, that is 335 rupees, upon my return from Port Said to Bom-
bay. We boarded the ship at nine o’clock on the morning of the first of
May. At approximately twelve o’clock, the ship raised anchor and, recit-
ing bismillāh majrīhā wa-mursāhā,
7 we said goodbye to Hindustan. There
were only five travelers in second class, and by a curious coincidence all of

18 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
them were from a different nation and a different race.8 That is, one Mus-
lim, one English, one Parsi, one Spanish, and one Siamese.
The Ocean Air. The motion of the ship did not seem too disagreeable at
first. But around evening, my constitution began to change for the worse.
I ate dinner and went to sleep. When my eyes opened in the morning, I
was in a strange state. The discomfort from dizziness and nausea was too
severe to describe. For two days, I remained in a state like that of fainting.
The ship attendant sometimes brought tea, biscuits, and tangerines, telling
me to eat something. But upon seeing those things, I would begin to retch.
Mr. Arnold always drank tea. Even though it did not stay down, [4] one
felt some relief by vomiting. At his insistence, I, too, drank tea a few times
and vomited, and felt some benefit. On the third day, we all recovered and
sprang to life. I had always heard that sea air was extremely beneficial for
one’s health and fitness. Truly, travel by ship stands out as one treatment
among a hundred treatments. I was weak and feeble up to the time that I
boarded. But with each passing day I became haler and heartier. My con-
stitution was always cheerful and I had quite an appetite. We were given
food five times a day, that is, tea, milk, and biscuits at eight o’clock in the
morning; ordinary food at eleven o’clock in which there were dishes of
numerous kinds; tiffin at one o’clock; dinner at five o’clock, in which, in
addition to ordinary meat, there were chicken, duck, pigeon, puddings of
every kind, and wet and dry fruits. Sometimes there was even kulfi.
9 Tea
and butter at nine o’clock at night. We ate our fill at every meal and every-
thing was digested.
A Christian’s Prejudice against the Arabic Language. I kept busy all
day, walking along, taking in the view of the sea. Mr. Arnold had begun
learning Arabic. The Spanish Christian who was with us used to become
heated about Mr. Arnold’s reading Arabic. He would often come to him
and pronounce the Arabic letters contemptuously in an extremely nasty
voice, and would say, “This language is the language of camels.” Although
I was offended by these actions of his, such treatment of Arabs and the
Arabic language by a nation that had lived with disgrace for a time under
the hand of Arabs was not inappropriate.

The Beginning of the Journey 19
Winged Animals Were Slaughtered in Accordance with Żabḥ. Because
it is generally reported that winged animals are not slaughtered according
to żabḥ on ships,10 and Maulawī Samī‘ullāh Khān ṣāḥib11 [5] has even con-
firmed this in his travelogue, I abstained from eating fowl meat for a few
days. Mr. Arnold asked me the reason for this. I said, “In our religion, an
animal killed by strangulation is haram.” He told me, “On this ship, fowl
are slaughtered with żabḥ. They are not killed by wringing their necks.”
Because, according to sharia, his testimony alone was not sufficient, I went
and confirmed this myself. The person doing the żabḥ was a Christian. He
did not recite anything at the time of żabḥ. He just slid the knife across
the throat. Although an animal slaughtered by this method of żabḥ is not
halal among the Ḥanafīs, for a few days I became a Shāfi‘ī on this issue,
according to whom every kind of żabīḥah is permissible.12
On the ship, Mr. Arnold was no longer the Arnold that he was in
Aligarh. Neither was there that seriousness, nor that standoffishness. He
would often laugh and joke, play with children, and skip and jump on the
deck. I began to write an ode13 about the circumstances of the trip, and in
fact the atmosphere of the ocean was so appealing and pleasant that a man
of suitable and balanced nature could not help but break into a hum on a
journey by ship.
The Despicable Actions of the Somali Nation. On May 7, 1892, the ship
arrived at Aden and dropped anchor at a distance from the shore. A very
interesting thing in Aden is that a great many boys of the Somali nation
aboard dinghies come close to the ship and make all kinds of strange, dis-
graceful movements for reward from the people on the ship. Some dance
and sing. Some come together and say a few meaningless words as they
play their armpits. The remarkable thing is that people toss whatever they
wish to reward them, do-annī, chau-annī, paise, into the ocean, and the
boys dive in and retrieve it. Most Europeans were engaged in the spec-
tacle, and Arnold, too, enjoyed it. But [6] my state was something differ-
ent, for I mistakenly thought that this place was generally populated by
Arabs. For this reason, it was natural that I should look at them with eyes
of respect and affection. But they made such unbefitting and disgrace-
ful movements for reward that my nature could in no way endure it. It

20 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
was like a cautionary lesson that the state of the Arabs was now such that
they were not ashamed to act this way in front of others. These thoughts
filled my heart with grief. So much so that tears flowed from my eyes and
qumm yā ‘Umar14 spontaneously issued from my tongue. Arnold was
nearby. He noticed the change in my state. I described the condition of
my heart and the reasons for it. Raising his eyes once, he looked at me and
fell silent. When, having gone into the city to investigate, it was proved by
all accounts that the Somali nation is not Arab, I was to some extent reas-
sured. This very anger and offense was the reason that I have harshly ridi-
culed this wretched nation in my travel ode and, in truth, it deserves it.15
Because time was short, I could not see the interior parts of the city. I
dispatched letters to Hindustan. On the heading of one letter I wrote these
couplets, which were composed just then:
When, intent on this journey, I girded my loins, with this intent of mine
I cast both enemies and friends into writhing and twisting.
All wondered: What is to be gained by it?
For what have I cast myself into such affliction?
Everyone gave me advice, and all said that I had,
With these words, cast a mask from the cheeks of meaning.
When they carried their insistence over the limit, I said, “Enough!
Let come what may! I have cast my boat into the water.”16
The Language of Aden. The language of Aden is generally Arabic, and the
Parsis, Hindus, and Bengalis, [7] who live here on account of commerce or
service, speak Arabic effortlessly. Because I had never heard the words of
this sacred language from the tongue of a Hindu, I felt a strange pleasure
seeing merchants and grocers17 saying, “ Aina tarūḥ? Mā tabghī?”18
The language here is Arabic, but it is extremely base and ineloquent.
Although classical Arabic no longer exists in any of the regions where
Arabic is spoken these days, the language of Aden is the most peculiar.
Except for a few ordinary words, I could not understand anything. Most
likely, the language of this place has reached this state after a period of
continual degradation because of admixture with foreigners. ‘Allāmah
[very learned] Muqaddasī,19 who was a renowned traveler of Arabia and
who traveled the world at the beginning of the fourth century, writes in

The Beginning of the Journey 21
his geography, “The nations that reside in Aden are mostly Persian.” The
aforementioned very learned scholar has also written, “They commonly
say kāf [k] instead of jīm [j] here, and rujlīnah instead of rujliyah,
20 and
so on.” When such was the state of things in the age of the ‘allāmah, what
complaint can be made about the language of this place after the mixture
of Marhat ˙
t
˙as and Gujaratis?
Strange and Wondrous Monkeys. In Aden, a German boarded our ship
who is an employee at a famous German museum and is returning to
Europe after living in these environs for some time.21 By virtue of travel
and trade, he was able to speak effortlessly in numerous languages. When
he conversed with the ship’s officers in Italian, Arnold in English, and me
in Arabic, I was seriously astonished and envious. When we all gathered
at the dinner table, he was the one who acted as everyone’s interpreter.
[8] He has collected many strange and wondrous animals from the jun-
gles of Arabia and Africa. In one large cage, there were African monkeys
whose appearance was somewhat different from ordinary monkeys. The
most wondrous thing about them was that when, seeing someone com-
ing toward them, they would cry out, and several letters seemed to come
from the sounds that they made. At first, I thought that they were made-
up words of some kind, just as we interpret the sound of cats as miyā’on,
for example. But several times, when I listened closely, I clearly sensed the
sound of l and yāyā. So much so that if some person had heard it from
behind a curtain, he could never have thought that it was the voice of a
monkey. When I mentioned this to Mr. Arnold, he, too, confirmed it.
Probably because of examples of this kind, the idea has occurred to several
people in Europe that monkeys, too, can speak. Thus, it is famously noted
that after a period of experiment and research, one ṣāḥib has discovered
several letters of this language.22
An Unpleasant Incident and Mr. Arnold’s Steadiness. Because in Aden
new things of interest had been found, we were traveling with great plea-
sure. But the very next day, a dangerous incident occurred which kept me
seriously worried for a while. When I awoke on the morning of May 10,
a fellow traveler said that the ship’s engine had broken. When I looked,

22 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
the captain and the ship’s employees were indeed worriedly pacing about
and were devising strategies to repair it. The engine had become com-
pletely useless, and the ship was moving along extremely slowly because
of the wind. I became terribly worried, and some extremely disagreeable
thoughts began to enter my mind. What else could I have done in this state
of panic? I ran to Mr. Arnold. At that time, he was reading a book with
extreme calm and composure. [9] I said, “Haven’t you heard the news!?”
He said, “Yes, the engine has broken.” I said, “Aren’t you panicked? What
kind of time is this to read a book?” He said, “If the ship is to be lost,
then this little bit of time is even more precious, and it is total stupidity to
squander such precious time.” Because of his steadiness and boldness, I
also felt reassured and regained composure. Eight hours later, the engine
was repaired and began to run as usual.
The ship arrived at Suez on May 13 and stayed for three or four hours.
Egyptian Arabs brought paneer, dates, and bread to sell. One of them,
understanding me to be Hindustani, began to speak with me in Urdu. I
was surprised, and when I learned by inquiry that he had never seen the
face of Hindustan, I was even more surprised at the worldwide reach of
Urdu. On May 14, we arrived at Port Said, and with much regret I was
forced to separate from Mr. Arnold. I had purchased a ticket to Brindisi
from Bombay. Having arrived at Port Said, I thought, “I am with Arnold
as far as Brindisi, but it is a week’s journey from there to Constantinople.
During that time, because I will have to deal with strangers and the for-
eign language and country, I will face difficulty in every task.” On the
basis of this thought, I changed the previous scheme entirely and decided
that I would go to Constantinople by way of Syria.
When the ship anchored, a Cook Company employee came aboard
to take care of his travelers. The ship stands at a bit of distance from the
shore. Thus, a very small boat provided by the Cook Company is always
ready to carry travelers ashore. [10] An inexperienced person faces serious
difficulty when disembarking the ship at these ports. With the anchoring
of the ship, coolies and sailors attack from every direction and seriously
harass the travelers. Amid their throng, noise, shouting, and the snatching
and seizing of luggage, travelers completely lose their senses. When, with a
thousand difficulties, one finally reaches the shore, the debate and dispute

The Beginning of the Journey 23
over the rate lasts for hours. An excellent way to remain safe from these
troubles is not to have any dealings with anyone except for the employees
of the Cook Company.
When we arrived on shore, Shemūyal [Samuel], who was already
standing waiting for us, stepped forward and shook hands with us. This
man is of the Jewish nation and is appointed to look after travelers and to
render them assistance of every kind. He knows numerous languages and
speaks Arabic, English, and French extremely effortlessly. The best part is
that he can speak in Urdu with extreme ease, the reason for which is that
he has lived for some time in Hindustan. We went with him to his office.
The office building is on the edge of the water and is nicely appointed with
a table and chairs. On the desk are always found a great many newspapers,
in which there is mostly news and advertisements related to ships. First,
we spoke with him about having the ticket changed, meaning that if we
disembarked here and bought a new ticket for Constantinople, could we
receive the additional rate that we had already paid as far as Brindisi as
a deduction or not? Because he could not answer the question himself,
he went into the company’s main office, and, upon returning, said, “You
can go to Constantinople on the same ticket. You will only have to pay
two pounds, meaning thirty-two rupees, more.” I was very pleased and
in reward for his good service gifted him eight rupees. [11] It was also a
happy coincidence that the ship going to Constantinople was ready at that
time. Otherwise, I would have had to remain at Port Said for fifteen days.
Port Said. Port Said is a small, beautiful port. The populated area has two
parts. European merchants generally live in the part that adjoins the sea,
and there are many large hotels, coffeehouses, theatres, and so on. One
coffeehouse is right on the seashore and is quite spacious and atmospheric.
Many small tables made of slabs of marble stone, and around them chairs,
have been arranged with extreme attention to order and detail. Coffee,
chai, toast, and butter are always available. The shops in this area are in
abundance, and they are extremely grand and well appointed. The original
residents of this place reside in the other part. But unfortunately, every-
thing is in an extremely poor state. Instead of hotels, there are the dirty
shops of cooks.

24 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Initially, when I left to tour the city, I viewed everything with eyes of
great interest and wonder because this was the first occasion on which I
saw a populated area of the sultanate of Islam. (I had already had the honor
of pilgrimage to Mecca and Medina, but that was the country of God, and
I am talking about a worldly sultanate and government).23 Whenever I
saw a tall and magnificent building, I would become happy at the thought
that “Praise be to God! In these regions, Muslims are prosperous and
wealthy!”24 But upon inquiry, I would learn that the building belonged to
a European merchant. Not one excellent store or tall building in the entire
city belonged to a Muslim. Alas!
In every land we reached, the sky is found.25
[12] Of course, there is a royal masjid at the end of the European settle-
ment, and it is quite lofty and magnificent.
After wandering around the marketplace for a little while, I boarded
the ship to Constantinople. Shemūyal and Mr. Arnold were with me. Be-
cause it was the time for ḥajj to Jerusalem, first and second classes were
both filled with Christian ḥājīs. Mr. Arnold said, “I fear lest you be trou-
bled. These people are strict adherents to their religious tradition, and
therefore they are certain to hold some prejudice. You are of another reli-
gion, another nation. How will these people tolerate your company?” But
from experience, I learned that Mr. Arnold was mistaken. Those people
were adherent to religion, but they were French and Italian. They were
not English. Thus, they lacked entirely the qualities of aloofness and the
distinction between conqueror and conquered that are the special charac-
teristics of a conquering nation. Mr. Arnold departed after a little while.
I said goodbye to him, and, along with that, had the worrisome thought,
“Let’s see how it goes now, all alone.”
On May 15, the ship arrived at Jaffa. Most of our European fellow
travelers disembarked here. Jerusalem is only a night’s journey from here.
Because time was short, I could not disembark here.
On May 16, we arrived at Beirut. The ship generally does not stop here
for less than two watches [six hours]. Because this is a historical place, and
it is an extremely ancient city, I was very keen to see it. Having arrived on

The Beginning of the Journey 25
shore, I was faced with the great difficulty that they did not let anyone dis-
embark there without a tażkirah, meaning a passport.26 I had left Hindustan
in such a hurry that I did not have an opportunity to obtain a passport.
First, I became very worried that I would miss out on the visit. But then an
idea came to me, and I said to the people, [13] “I do not want to stay here.
My intention was only to visit.” One of them, God knows how, recognized
that I was from Hindustan. Thinking me to be far from home, he treated me
kindly and sent a person with me: “He will take you on a tour of the city.”
A Visit to Beirut. Because it was already my intention to stay here for a
day or two on my return from Constantinople, I only cursorily toured the
marketplace, and so on, this time. I looked through bookstores. There was
a coffeehouse on the main thoroughfare. I stopped there for a little while
and watched the passersby. Whenever a person passed in front of me in a
carriage or on horseback with great glory and grandeur, I would ask my
guide who it was, and he would mostly respond, “Christian.”
The thing I liked most here was that all the shop owners and profes-
sionals, even the coolies and laborers, were extremely well dressed and
clean clothed. After strolling around for three or four hours, I returned. I
gave the guide an eight-anna tip, and, having taken leave of him, boarded
the ship.
From Port Said, a Change in the Condition of the Journey. The nov-
elty that occurred in the circumstances of the journey from Port Said was
that, from Bombay to Port Said, there was no Muslim on the ship. Having
arrived here, I caught a glimpse of one or two Muslims, and, in Beirut, the
entire ship filled up with Syrian Arabs. Unfortunately, this honor did not
fall to the lot of first and second class, but in third class there were Mus-
lims and only Muslims in every direction. I had longed to see the faces
of Muslims since the outset of the journey. Upon seeing this crowd, my
happiness knew no bounds. The deck of first class was an extremely clean
and spacious place, and I often sat there and took in the ocean view. But
when this company fell to my lot, I did not set foot there again, not even
by mistake. [14]

26 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Initially, I met with severe difficulty in making friends with these
people. These people were spread out all around the deck, and there were
separate groups of two to four people each. I very eagerly approached
them, but they paid absolutely no attention to me. Whomever I stood
near raised his eyes toward me once and lowered his head. I was seri-
ously stunned at this rudeness. I said in my heart, “And I had heard such
praises of the hospitality of the Arabs! They have trouble making even
casual conversation.” Among them were several students from the Mili-
tary College who had come to their homeland on break and now were
going to Constantinople.27 They sometimes read an Arabic dīwān, and so
on, to amuse themselves. I thought that I should produce some acquain-
tance with them by means of our sharing a field of learning. Thus, I went
to them and began to make a show of my maulawiyat and knowledge.
Even then, they did not pay attention to me. I returned, feeling foolish
and at a loss. But I was certain that there must be some reason for this. As
it happened, one person asked me my religion. I said, “Islam.” He said,
“Lā! Wa-Allāh! A hāżā ṭarbūsh al-Muslim?”28 meaning, “No! Would a
Muslim ever wear such a cap?” Unfortunately, there was an Iranian cap
on my head, and for this reason all the Arabs thought I was a Magian.
When this mystery was solved, I removed the suspicion from their hearts
and we became as inseparable as milk and sugar. So much so that they
did not want to be apart from me for even a single breath. I mostly kept
company with the students of the Madrasah-i Ḥarbiyah. From them, I
learned some very important things about Constantinople, and, in truth,
I benefitted greatly from the information.
The Effect of Islamic Government. The effect of our now being in the
Islamic world was also noticeable on the ship. From Bombay to Suez, [15]
the travelers in third class were treated like coolies. But in these regions,
the situation changed entirely. Whatever the ship’s officers and employees,
who are generally European, thought of the travelers in their hearts, they
could not mistreat them outwardly. There were numerous occasions on
which I saw that it was the Muslims who were out of line, but the officers
of the ship were forced to turn a blind eye.

The Beginning of the Journey 27
Cyprus. On May 17, the ship arrived at Cyprus.* This is a small island,
which is located in the Sea of Turkey, and which they call Qubruṣ in Ara-
bic. This island is a monument of the classical conquests of Islam. Amīr
Mu‘āwiyah attacked it in the time of Ḥaz¨rat ‘Us˙mān (ra) in 27 Hijrī [647–
48].29 The people of the city signed a treaty declaring that, “Just as we give
tribute to the sultanate of Turkey, we shall give you, too, 7,200 dinars per
year, and if ever there is war between you and the Romans, we will not
have any involvement with anyone.” Amīr Mu‘āwiyah accepted this con-
dition. But in 32 Hijrī [652–53], those people, against their promise, gave
assistance to the Romans against the Muslims. The aforementioned amīr
attacked again with a fleet of five hundred ships and conquered it with
extreme ease. Still, he allowed the amount of tribute and the conditions of
the truce to remain the same. On his order, twelve thousand Arabs went
and settled there and built buildings and masjids. After some time, this
island fell from the hand of the Muslims, and, having been conquered sev-
eral times, was lost again. At last, the Turks took it back from the Christians
in 1570, and it was in their control until recently. In the last war between
Turkey and Russia, the English took it on the condition [16] that the sulṭān
would continue to receive the yearly tribute that he used to receive.30 Thus,
now there is English rule and English administration there.
Larnaca [Larnakah] and Limassol [Limāmūn] are two large cities on
this island, and the ship anchors at both places for a short while. I visited
Limassol. Because there is English governance here, there was no pass-
port inquiry and inspection. When I entered the city, I was wearing an
Iranian cap on my head and a shirwānī achkan on my body.31 The people
there probably had never seen this fashion. Wherever I passed by, people
would look at me in wonder, and wherever I stood, a crowd of specta-
tors would form. I first went into the congregational masjid. There is a
*
It is written in books of geography that in the classical age there were 9 districts, 12
cities, 805 villages, and 10 lākh residents on this island. The Turks seized it in 1570. Now
there are seventy thousand inhabitants. Larnaca’s wine is extremely famous, and its silk,
too, is quite excellent.

28 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
school adjacent to the masjid. There, a maulawī ṣāḥib, who was extremely
dignified and well dressed, was giving lessons to the elementary ranks.
I greeted him with salām ‘alaik [peace be upon you]. He stood up and,
responding to my greeting with extreme kindness, indicated for me to
sit. The boys were seated on tripod stools. I, too, sat down beside them. At
the maulawī’s indication, one boy read several verses of the Holy Quran.
A wondrous effect came over my heart. I thought, “How could one even
compare that desert of Hijaz with the distant islands in the Sea of Tur-
key?! What effect was there in this sacred word (the Quran) that, like
electric force, it raced from the East to the West and still remains today?”
That innocent boy also had a nice voice and read in accordance with the
principles of recitation. As it happened, the verses were also effective.
These things rendered me half-conscious, and for a while I was overcome
by a strange, wondrous state.
Although the English have been ruling here for fifteen or sixteen years,
they have maintained a great many old things in the style of administra-
tion with regard to policy. [17] The department of qaz¨ā is entirely sepa-
rate, and the English government has no involvement with sharia cases.32
I happened to pay my respects to the qāz¨ī ṣāḥib. He is a very polite and
dignified person. The method of education, too, is entirely in accordance
with the Turkish system. In all the schools and madrasas, the books of
the Turkish Department of Education are taught. In the school that I
just mentioned, the Holy Quran, an introductory tract on fiqh [jurispru-
dence], history, and geography are included in the course, and instruction
takes place in an extremely fine manner. I also visited this school when
returning from Constantinople. It was in the morning, and the instruc-
tor ṣāḥib had not yet come at that time. Two or three boys were present.
They treated me with extreme respect and good manners. One asked me,
“Where is your homeland?” I said, “Hindustan.” He said, “Hindustan is a
vast region. Please tell me the name of the city, specifically.” I mentioned
Aligarh. He began to say, “I will see on the map where it is located.” A
map of Hindustan was hanging in front. He took a brief look at it and
immediately set his finger on Aligarh and said, “Yes, this is it!” He was
not more than nine or ten years old. Accordingly, I was surprised by his
sharpness and memory. I asked, “Who is your king?” He said, “ Āfandim.”

The Beginning of the Journey 29
In Turkish, āfandī is synonymous with “lord and master.” And when the
first-person m is affixed, then the sulṭān is generally meant. I said, “But
the English are ruling here.” He said, “Yes, they have taken it on lease and
they pay an annual tribute.” The policy and practical philosophy [18] of the
British is extremely wise, that when they seize control of a region, they do
it so gradually and mildly that the people of the region are not even aware
of the regime change.
The language of this place is Turkish, and this is also the language
of every city and town from here to Constantinople. One can estimate
the dominance of the rule of the Turks from the fact that they changed
even the language of the conquered regions. Asia Minor is such a vast
region, and an abundance of Christians reside in it whose language at
some time was Greek or Latin, but now Turkish is spoken throughout
the entire region. Although the maulawī ṣāḥib and qāz¨ī ṣāḥib of Cyprus,
whom I mentioned, knew Arabic well, they could not speak it. Of course,
they could understand ordinary sentences, and I spoke with them relying
on these.
What accurate estimate of the state of the Muslims of this place could
I have gained in such a short time? But by appearances one can reason that
it is not good. Upon inquiry, I learned that whatever tall buildings and fine
stores I saw all belonged to Christians.
The ship reached Rhodes on May 18 and stayed for three or four
hours. This is a very small island whose extent our classical historians have
described as sixty miles, and in the geography translated by the Aligarh
Society, the length is written as forty miles and the width fifteen miles.33
This, too, is among the classical conquests. It was conquered in the time
of Amīr Mu‘āwiyah in 52 Hijrī [672], and at that time many Muslims went
and settled there. I was eager to visit it on account of its antiquity, but
unfortunately it was nighttime [19] and none of the people on the ship
would go with me. An even greater misfortune was that, as it happened,
the same reasons confronted me on the return trip, and I was left entirely
deprived of a visit to it.
On the morning of May 20, we arrived at Izmir. Because this is a very
large port, the ship remained here for two days. I disembarked with my
Syrian friends. There was the same tażkirah inquiry on the shore, but

30 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
thanks to my companions, I did not have much trouble. This city, which in
English they call Smyrna, is the headquarters of Asia Minor, and no city in
this district is more expansive and populous. It is also a monumental loca-
tion with regard to antiquity and historical events. The grave of Homer,
who was a famous poet of Greece and about whom the thought of Europe
is that he was the greatest poet in the world, is right here. One of the seven
churches that are mentioned in the Book of Revelation in the New Testa-
ment was in this city. The vicissitudes of time have destroyed it ten times.
Still, its current population is greater than one lakh. The land in the area
is extremely fertile, and the city itself is a major center of trade. Scores of
steamships and sailboats are always present in the port. The rail, too, runs
here, and the train departs from here twice a day.
Islamic monuments are in abundance. People have recounted to me
that the number of masjids is no less than three hundred, among which
some are of great glory and grandeur.
When we disembarked the ship, we saw a series of extremely tall and
glorious [20] buildings that stretched far into the distance in a straight
line along the sea. These buildings are hotels, coffeehouses, dance houses,
and the shops of Christian traders, and are extremely beautiful, spacious,
and full of atmosphere. At night, it always seems that there is some fes-
tival or a wedding party. In addition to the coffeehouses and the dance
houses, there is always a large crowd on the street, and wherever you go,
you hear the sound of singing and sarod. Behind this series of buildings is
the neighborhood of the Christians, and there are such tall and glorious
buildings as I had never seen before. All the lanes and alleys of this neigh-
borhood are extremely clean and level.
Having finished my tour of this neighborhood, I turned toward the
city. Although the city is extremely vibrant and seems like a festival because
of the large number of people, all the streets are uneven and unclean, and
it is difficult to walk down the street because of the filth and mud. The
reality is that in all these regions, the administration of the municipality
is extremely bad, and this matter is extremely worthy of the attention of
the Turkish government. As we were walking, our Syrian friends became
hungry, and we went and sat at the shop of a nān-bā’ī [baker]. I did not
have an appetite, but I joined at their insistence. By the word baker, our

The Beginning of the Journey 31
readers will probably have thought of the bakers of India and their vile
shops. But this supposition is not correct. The look of the appointments at
the most ordinary of ordinary shops here is that numerous small tables,
and chairs around them, are arranged. An extremely clean sheet is spread
on the tables. A tap is set up in one corner of the wall, and beneath it a
basin, and to the right side, soap and a towel are laid out. This is the condi-
tion of extremely ordinary shops, and the large shops, [21] which can be
called hotels [restaurants], are extremely elaborate and magnificent. But
all the hotels of this kind generally belong to Christians.
I tried to tour the madrasas, but because it was Friday, all the madra-
sas were closed. I performed namāz at the Hisar Congregational Mosque
[Jāmi‘ Ḥiṣār].34 This masjid is ceremonious and decorated. There is gilt
ornamentation on the ceiling. The great virtue of this masjid is that bells
are set on two large pillars on both sides of the courtyard because of which,
in addition to knowing the timings of namāz, the masjid is also decorated.
It would be good if this were imitated in our Hindustan. There are several
innovations in the sermons and namāz here, but neither do they have any
basis in the sharia, nor are they suitable in their own right. When the
preacher reads the sermon, he regularly stops in the middle, and at that
time several people recite something in unison. When they become silent,
the preacher begins again, and this happens several times. They generally
read short sūras in namāz, which are not more than three or four āyats,
even though throughout the entire world it is customary to read long sūras
in Friday namāz.
After finishing with namāz, I went into the library. This is not a large
library. It is a very small room in the corner of the masjid, and there are
three or four small cabinets of books. After namāz, most ‘ulamā and
authors come and sit here. When I arrived, the following people were
present: Maulānā Muṣṭafā Āfāndī, imam of the Congregational Masjid
and instructor at the madrasa; Ṣabrī Āfandī, teacher at the i‘dādī school;35
Maulānā Sa‘īd; Shukrī Bey; and Ḥusnī Afandī, former secretary of educa-
tion.36 [22] After salām and standard greetings, one ṣāḥib declared, “We
were just talking about an issue. If you wish, let the issue be raised again.”
I gladly agreed. It was a debate about mut‘ah,
37 and the same famous point
of uncertainty was before us that it is proven by the word of Ḥazrat ‘Umar

32 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
(ra) himself that the custom of temporary marriage was current in the
lifetime of the Prophet (saas). I discussed it in some detail and every-
one present agreed. These people did not understand Arabic, so I spoke
in Persian. This custom of debate and discussion is commonly practiced
in these regions and is an extremely polite and proper custom. A foreign
person has no easier and more beneficial means of meeting a group of
‘ulamā and producing a connection and intimacy with them. Its great
virtue is that disputation does not take place by reason of egotism and
arrogance; rather, if during the discussion they come to know, by means
of the addressee’s manner, that he cannot successfully discharge his duty
in the debate, then they purposefully bring up another topic. Intellectual-
scientific assemblies of this kind were a major means of my success on this
journey, and, in some places, thanks to them alone I obtained deliverance
from difficulties from which there was no other means of escape.
The ship raised anchor around evening on May 21. There is no large
station from here to Constantinople. The ship stopped at a few places for a
short time each, but we could not disembark. These places are mostly for
the necessities of war, and at each place the instruments of war are assem-
bled in abundance. Chanāq Qil‘ah [Çanakkale] is one place where there is
an extremely secure fort. People recounted to me that when Muḥammad
Fātiḥ38 decided to conquer Constantinople, [23] cannons and cannonballs
were not generally in use, and Muḥammad cast cannons himself and had
clay cannonballs made, some of which have survived as memorials. These
cannonballs are well built and extremely strong, and it is recounted that
they are no less than iron cannonballs. From Izmir to Constantinople,
such secure fortresses and barrier walls have been set up on both sides of
the sea, and the provisions of war are in such abundance, that even the
most powerful of powerful sultanates cannot attempt to attack the capital
by this route. All these fortresses and fortifications are from the age of
Muḥammad Fātiḥ. When this renowned emperor went forth with the plan
to capture Constantinople, he had military cantonments built all around
and had fortresses and barrier walls prepared. (But all the details in this
section are peoples’ oral reports. I have not confirmed this in the history.)
Moving beyond Chanāq Qil‘ah, we saw a strange spectacle. The ship
was moving quickly when from afar something appeared to be erupting

The Beginning of the Journey 33
like a fountain in the water. After a little while, I learned that four or five
fish were racing toward the ship. When they came near, they joined the
ship. One could clearly see their body through the surface of the water.
Although the ship was going extremely fast, they kept right along with
it. Sometimes, when they would gasp, they would hiss loudly, and at that
time one could see something like a fountain erupting in the water. They
raced alongside the ship for nearly two miles. All the people watched the
spectacle in wonder. Several had the idea, “These fish have never seen the
form of a ship. Thus, they thought it was some animal, and, in the passion
of competition, [24] did not want the ship to be able to outrun them.” Dur-
ing my return trip, too, just such an incident occurred, and at that time I
discovered that the fish had happened to come to this place one time, and
the ship’s employees tossed something into the sea for them to eat. Greedy
for this, whenever a ship passes through here, these fish often appear and
race alongside the ship for a distance.
We arrived at Constantinople in the morning on May 23. The ship
anchored. This was a time at which I should have been extremely happy
to arrive at my destination, but in the commotion and shouting of the
coolies and boatmen, I lost my senses; and the boatmen surrounded the
entire ship. With their shouting, pushing, and shoving, a strange commo-
tion had arisen. I had not determined beforehand, nor could I, where to go
after disembarking the ship. A hotel was not appropriate to my situation
(the reason for this will be made known later), and because of my foreign-
ness and unfamiliarity, I could not be assured of or rely upon serais. The
serious difficulty was that my Syrian friends, from whom assistance of
every kind could have been expected, were in a hurry to reach the college.
Thus, they could not wait for me. Finding me alone, the boatmen and coo-
lies began to harass me even more. My distress continued to grow from
the thought that if I had this much trouble on the ship on account of the
foreignness of the language, how would things be in the city? It became
later and later in this dawdle and delay. Most of the travelers had disem-
barked the ship and continued to disembark. Finally, I turned my luggage
over to the steward and told him, “I shall return having toured the city.”
My intention was first to go into the city to make some arrangement for
my stay, [25] then to remove my things from the ship. Some Arabs from

34 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Syria had rented a boat. I, too, went along with them. There was passport
inquiry and inspection on the shore. I showed my English papers, but they
asked for a passport. In short, with a thousand difficulties, I was released.
Now I was confused as to where I should go. On the boat, I was introduced
to a Syrian Arab whose name was ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ.
39 I described my distress
to him and said, “Please, tell me some reasonable way to proceed.” He
said, “My situation is nearly the same as yours. Thus, it is best that we stay
together.” Although this course of action was opposed to caution, I had to
adopt it because of my unfamiliarity and the foreignness of the language.
And if you ask the truth, this chance company was the preface of all my
future success.
Hotels, Serais, and Places for Rent. There are several manners of lodging
for travelers here. The greatest surety and ease is in hotels. However, firstly,
their rate is no less than one pound, that is, fifteen rupees, per day. And
second, most—rather, nearly all—the excellent hotels are in the European
area, which is far from Istanbul, and all the congregational masjids, librar-
ies, madrasas, and schools are in Istanbul.
After hotels there are khānāt, that is, serai, but these serais have no
relation to Hindustan. Here, all the rooms in large serais are generally
large, spacious, and attractive, and a bed made of woven strips, toshak
mattress, sheets, blanket, and necessary things are always furnished in
them. [26] There are several beds in each room, and the rate is eight or ten
annas per bed.
The third method is rental houses. These houses are typically two
or three stories. On each level are numerous rooms, and in each room,
a table, chair, couch, lamp, carpet, bed, mattress, pillow, and blanket are
provided. The rent per room is typically from ten rupees per month to
twenty or thirty. The owners or leaseholders of these houses are generally
Christian. They themselves also live in these houses, and because of them,
travelers experience a great deal of ease.
Although, as I have just described, taking a house on rent would have
been the easier option, my Syrian friend and I were both unaware of it.
Thus, we went and stayed in a khān, meaning a serai. When I was satis-
fied with this arrangement, I went back onto the ship and had my luggage

The Beginning of the Journey 35
removed and brought. We lived in that khān for six or seven days. Then we
took an excellent house near the Bāb-i ‘ālī on rent.
The Circumstances of Shaikh ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ. Fortunately, Shaikh ‘Abd
al-Fattāḥ, with whom I made friends by compulsion, turned out to be a
person from a very esteemed family. Ḥaz¨rat Shaikh Khālid Naqshbandī
was a revered elder in Damascus to whom the people here are so devoted
that they do not utter his name, rather, they refer to him with the word
ḥaz¨rat [his majesty].40 This elder was nurtured in the pure soil of our Hin-
dustan. That is, he was a disciple of Mirzā Jān-i Jānān Dihlawī.41 Shaikh
‘Abd al-Fattāḥ is his fraternal nephew, and [27] because of this relation-
ship, people hold him in high esteem. Because there is a large group of
Syrians in Constantinople, ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ became acquainted with most
people within just a few days, and, by means of him, I, too, was introduced
to them in turn.
Meeting Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān. One day, Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān, whose father
is a famous Ṣūfī, came to meet Shaikh ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ. I, too, was present
at the time, and it just so happened that the tract Iskāt al-Mu‘tadī, which
is an old work of mine and is in Arabic, was lying in front of us.42 Pick-
ing it up, he looked at it and said, “Aha! I saw this tract some time ago at
my shaikh’s place in Damascus, and he said of its author, “Shakkar Allāh
masa’‘iyah.”43 When Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān learned that the tract was writ-
ten by none other than me, he stood up and embraced me with passionate
warmth and treated me with extreme grace and kindness. I was extremely
delighted by the fact that my insignificant writing had come all the way
here and people looked upon it with eyes of acceptance, and in the loneli-
ness of the journey, such a means of introduction felt like a great blessing.
Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān is a young man. He was educated in fiqh by Shaikh
‘Abd al-Raḥmān, who was the maternal grandson and student of the
author of Radd al-muḥtār (known as Shāmī [the Syrian]).44 Although he
has aptitude in most of the current sciences, he has the greatest mastery in
literature. He presented an undotted qaṣīdah in praise of the sulṭān, upon
which he received reward and recompense. He has been a guest of Dar-
wesh Pāshā for some time and the aforementioned pāshā treats him as a

36 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
dear friend.45 His relationship with me grew stronger by the day. So much
so that despite the great distance, he would come to my place nearly every
day and sometimes would stay with me for the entire day. [28] Shaikh ‘Abd
al-Fattāḥ returned to Damascus after a few days. Alone, I might perhaps
have run into hardship at that time, but Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān’s sympathies
removed all anxiety from my heart.
Although the house that we had taken on rent was extremely spacious,
attractive, and elegant, because the landlord (temporary) was extremely dis-
honest in business and vagrant in temperament, after a few days, I took
another house on rent and stayed there until the end. Here, not only was the
place very nice, but it was also a great comfort that the landlord was a kind-
natured woman. Although she was Christian and was of the Italian nation,
she could speak Arabic as needed and had special closeness with Muslims.
We had no need for arrangements for food and drink. Hotels and
shops are in abundance, and they are extremely neat and elaborate. To eat
in the marketplace is absolutely not a matter of disgrace here. I often saw
esteemed officials eating in hotels. These hotels generally belong to Chris-
tians. The shops of Muslims, except that there are also chairs and tables
there, in all other respects resemble the shops of Hindustan.
The qaṣīdah that I began to write on the ship came to completion upon
arrival at Constantinople. Included in it is a summary sketch of the cir-
cumstances of the journey, and because readers, having become familiar
with the details of all the circumstances, will be able to understand well
the allusions in the qaṣīdah that require a backstory and will take more
enjoyment and pleasure in it, I copy the qaṣīdah in its entirety here. [29]
Ode46
For both the completion of my subject and in search of edification,47
For ages it has been my intention to travel.
Having fulfilled the duty of ḥajj and pilgrimage by God’s decree,
I desired to journey to Turkey.
Although I burned with desire and was eager to make haste,
By the dictates of fate, postponement continued.
There was such a delay that the spiteful said,

The Beginning of the Journey 37
“So-and-so has nothing in his head but half-baked desire.
As if Turkey were just two or three steps away, this dreamer of half-baked
dreams
Has, without a care, tightly girded his loins for the journey.
The path is so long and the journey so perilous;
How is it achievable by one who has neither power nor gold?”
I worried and suffered greatly in this frustration and grief.
Suddenly, the manifestation of my desire walked through the door.
There took place a wondrous coincidence which unraveled this knot,
Of which even imagination and thought were unaware.
A couple of months before I beat the drum of departure,
My heart was frail and burnt from the strife of fever.
When I became weak with fever, it occurred to my heart,
“There is no remedy but a change of place, here and now.”
I remembered my longstanding intent and thought it would be nice
If the Lord accomplished two tasks in a single act.
Arnold, who is both my colleague and my teacher,
Also planned to travel to England at the time.
I thought to myself, “Such company and such an occasion rarely occur.”
Thus, I leapt eagerly from my place, intent on this journey.
When all became aware of my intention,
News also spread to friends and dear ones at home.
The kindness of all was stirred, and hearts ached.
All said, “Do not go to this useless trouble. [30]
Do not set hearts in separation; and do not forsake the way of fidelity.
And if you will not retreat from this path,
Rest a few days, then arrange
The provisions of the journey in a way that is suitable.
Take enough cash and goods with you that
There will be no danger or worry if you stay long.
It is best not to make this journey alone;
You must also bring along a servant.”
I said, “All that you have said is a wise counsel,
But the seeker-student is not in the game of profit and loss.
When a man takes a step forth at this stage,

38 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
He does not withdraw it, even if it brings death.”
In short, it was from the twenty-sixth of Ramz¨ān that I
Rose fervently from my place and set out upon my journey.
For a time I traveled through mountains and deserts,
Then I and other friends boarded a ship.
I endured trouble and hardship for two or three days on the ship,
It so rose and fell at every moment because of the waves.
No one had the power to lift his head from his pillow.
No one had the power to separate his body from his bed.
Nothing on the ship causes torment
Except for this three-day trial, from which there is no escape.
Bread and foods of every kind were available to us,
Lamb kabob and chicken and wine and fruits and sweets.
Although I did not pollute my lip with that pure wine,
Others, by contrast, quaffed from the goblet.
On the seventh of May, when we reached Aden,
The ship came to rest and dropped anchor for a while.
I disembarked and turned toward the city
In order to find information about the desert and towns of this region.
It is a mountainous area, in which, although it is high and vast,
There is no trace of greenery or flowers.
Every place you pass by, there is flowing sand and clay.
Every place you go, there is black dust and stone. [31]
The Guebres and Christians48 who have settled in this place
Spoke entirely in the Arabic language.
The people of the city, who call themselves Somali,
Are animals. No. In fact, they are even worse than animals.
Wretched, ill-fated, ruinous, black-skinned, and disgusting.
Vile, contemptible, perverse, and bad both by substance and by birth.
They have attached themselves to Arabia, but heaven forbid that
The Lord approve of such base and vile ones!
Because the language of all is Tāzī [Arabic] and, just like the Arabs,
Their name is tied to the title of their ancestors and fathers,
Common people fall into error and incorrectly believe
That they are from the lineage and descent of Ma‘d and Muz¨ar.49

The Beginning of the Journey The seed, and the roots, too, of this tree are from the soil of Ḥabash;50
It has bloomed and scattered fruit in this place.
In the evening, our ship set out again
And passed through the Red Sea for a week.
It came to Suez and came to a stop and it happened so quickly
That I was not aware of its condition or state.
This is that wondrous channel, of such a feat
I had never heard except in ancient tales;
It is twenty leagues long and so wide
That two steamships can pass through it.
A Frenchman named Lesseps51
Designed it and became famous throughout the world.
When in the beginning that wise man made the claim
That one could bring the task to completion,
The people mocked him and said that this
Was foolishness which no wise person would believe.
It was from the fourteenth of May that we arrived
At Port Said and boarded another ship.
Separation befell Arnold and me,
For my path and his parted at this crossing.
The port is a place filled with skiffs, boats, and steamships
As far as the eye can see. [32]
See a hundred that have raised flag here;
See a hundred that have dropped anchor there.
In the evening, our ship set sail again and passed
By way of Jaffa and then stopped at Beirut.
I went ashore and a man of the sons of Aleppo
Accompanied me and became my guide in every quarter.
It is a nice place where he cannot help but give away his heart
Who has fervor and passion in it.
It is a pleasant place, a fine spot to visit, and an attractive location:
Roads, even; land, clean; buildings, spectacular.
Giaours and Muslims alike, all well dressed and fine in form.
Elite and common, all rose-hued bodies and beautiful faces.
Their clothes resemble Arabia, as do their uniform and dress.
39

40 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
There is no difference between Muslim and nonbeliever.
When I left this place, it was because I had no choice.
I went ahead and my eye turned back once more.
It was the sixteenth of May when we departed.
Then at dawn we reached Cyprus.
This is the ancient place which, in the age of Amīr (meaning Amīr
Mu‘āwiyah),52
An army went to seize, and victory was augured.
At present, the government of England has taken it from the Turks,
But in peaceful treaty, not by aid of sword and hatchet.
I saw the congregational masjid and palace of Cyprus.
My visit to this place gave rise to more wondrous signs.
Rhodes and Chios53 appeared along the way, and, after that, Izmir.
The ship stopped at Izmir and spent one night there.
I went to the city and saw, one by one,
Masjid, school, market, street, alley, and door.
I performed my Friday duty and, after prayers,
I happened to pass by the sulṭānī library.
An assembly of jurisprudents was gathered there.
A discussion of mut‘ah and the words of ‘Umar was underway.54
One of them turned toward me, “How are you? What are you?
Why have you tied the garment of toil at your waist?” [33]
I said, “I am from Hind, a beggar for crumbs from the table of culture;55
I carry away something from every place and country.”
He said, “Just now discussion of mut‘ah was underway, and you, too,
If you can, should speak a few words and give example.”
In response, I knocked on the door of meaning and the audience
Opened lips of praise after debate and deliberation.
Then I departed from Izmir and in the span of two days
This route was traversed, and this volume reached its end.
I have written these letters briefly, and you, too, know
That in this lonely wilderness, the traveler is in straits.
Anyone who seeks the circumstances and details of me and my journey
Should be told to read this poem from end to end.

Summary History and Brief Circumstances
of Constantinople
2020. Syracuse University Press.
All rights reserved. May not be reproduced in any form without permission from the publisher, except fair uses permitted under U.S. or applicable copyright law.
Summary Ancient History of Constantinople. Before I give an account
of the detailed circumstances of this place under separate headings, it is
necessary that I give an account of its ancient history extremely briefly,
and, along with that, its general present circumstance with cursoriness.
The initial history of this city (meaning when it used to be called Byzan-
tium) is extremely ancient, but not a very short period of time has passed
since its name has been Constantinople.1 Constantine the Great laid its
foundation in 476, and from that time until the age of Muḥammad Fātiḥ
[Mehmet the Conqueror], it remained the seat of the throne of the Cae-
sars of Rome [Rūm (Turkey, Byzantium)]. Its circumstances are found
in extreme detail in English and present Islamic geographies. It is also
mentioned in classical Islamic geographies. However, except for Ibn-i
Baṭūṭah, I do not know of any Islamic author who has written an eyewit-
ness account of the events of that time.2 [34] Ibn-i Baṭūṭah saw this city
in 725 Hijrī [1324–25]. At that time, there was a Christian government
here. He writes, “This is an extremely magnificent city, and because it is
divided by a channel of water, it has been separated into two parts. One
part, which is on the eastern shore of the channel, is called Istanbūl, and
this is the part in which the Caesar of Rome and the members of govern-
ment and amīrs live. The other part is named Ghalaṭah. The great traders
of Europe generally live in it, whom the Caesar forcibly keeps in his obe-
dience.”3 Ibn-i Baṭūṭah has praised the extent of trade of these merchants
and ridiculed their filthiness. He writes, “When I entered this city, in
addition to small boats, nearly one hundred large ships were present, but
41
EBSCO Publishing: eBook Collection (EBSCOhost) printed on 2/20/2026 7:34:21 PM UTC via UNIVERSITY OF PITTSBURGH 1942825; Shibli Numani; Turkey, Egypt,
and Syria : A Travelogue Account:ehost.
42 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
the entire market is extremely dirty and foul, and even the churches are
no exception to this.”*
Muslims had looked upon it with eyes of conquest in the very first
century. Thus, the first to strike a sword on the iron door of the city walls,
‘Abdullāh bin al-Muṭṭalib,4 was the general of Caliph Walīd bin ‘Abd al-
Malik.5 After that, other caliphs and sulṭāns also attacked it. But the end
of the Caesar of Rome was to be at the hands of Muḥammad Fātiḥ, who
raised the standard of Islam in place of the cross above this magnificent
capital of the sultanate in 857 Hijrī [1453]. The thing about this aston-
ishing conflict that is worth remembering is that because the Christians
had blocked the way to the port by sea, the Turks [35] spread out wooden
boards for five miles on the rocky terrain that lies between the Bosphorus
and the Golden Horn, and, by driving ships to which they had attached
wheels across it, conveyed all the armies to the Golden Horn. At that time,
the age of this renowned Fātiḥ was twenty-three years. The chronogram of
the conquest is baldatun ṭayyibatun.
6
Present Condition. The present condition is that the city is settled on
both shores of the branch of the Bosphorus Strait, which stretches far off
into the distance, and for this reason it has two parts. One part is called
Istanbul, and all the large masjids, libraries, and tombs of the sulṭāns are
in this part. The population of Muslims, too, is in abundance here. The
second part begins with Perah, and at its far side are located Bashikṭāsh
[Beşiktaş], and so on, where the sulṭān’s royal palace and the hall of justice
are. On the other side of Perah [Pera] is Ghalaṭah [Galata], and because all
the major European traders and consuls of the sultanate reside here, it is
more appropriate to call it the European settlement.
They say that no city in the world is as scenic as Constantinople, and the
truth is that with respect to scenery, one cannot even imagine being more
beautiful than this. For this reason, they call its harbor “Golden Horn” in
English, meaning sunahrī sīng.
7 Here and there, a series of buildings lies
*
I have copied Ibn-i Baṭūṭah’s description so that you would be able to compare it
with the present state of things.

Constantinople 43
right on the edge of the sea and stretches far off into the distance. The land
that is in front of the buildings is extremely level and clean. Its surface is
perfectly even with the surface of the sea, and a stunningly beautiful scene
has been produced there.
An estimate of the extent and civic development of the city can be
made from the fact that in Istanbul alone there are five hundred congrega-
tional masjids, [36] 171 bathhouses, 324 serais, 164 classical madrasas, 500
modern madrasas, 12 colleges, 45 libraries, 305 hostels, and 48 printing
presses. There is such an abundance of business and traffic that numerous
tramways, public cars, twelve steamships, an underground rail, and ordi-
nary rails (which leave after every half hour), run at all times, and despite
this, there is still such a crowd of pedestrians on the streets that it seems
like a festival at all times. The toll for crossing the bridge that lies between
Ghalaṭah and Istanbul is one paisa per person. Its daily income is no less
than five or six thousand rupees.
Coffeehouses. Coffeehouses are in extreme abundance. In my estima-
tion, there must be no fewer than four or five thousand. Several of them,
whose buildings seem like royal palaces, are extremely magnificent. All
kinds of sherbets, chai, and coffee, and so on, are always available in the
coffeehouses. Most coffeehouses are on the seashore, and some are right
in the sea, for which a wooden bridge has been built. Daily newspapers,
too, are available in the coffeehouses. People go on drinking coffee as they
read the newspaper. In Constantinople—rather, in all these regions—
coffeehouses are counted among the necessities of life. When my Arab
friends heard from me that there is no such custom in Hindustan, they
used to say in astonishment, bi-aish yatasallūn,
8 meaning, how do peo-
ple amuse themselves there? In these regions, coffeehouses are places for
meeting with friends, and for the warmth and passion of company and
conversation.
Alas, Hindustanis have no taste for such things. They just do not know
[37] how necessary public intercourse of this kind is for the pleasure of
life and what kind of effect it has on the uplifting of one’s constitution.
Friendly assemblies take place in our area, too, the method of which is
that a few friends sometimes come to sit together at the house of a friend.

44 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
But there are two great defects in this method. First, sessions of entertain-
ment should take place in atmospheric locations so that bodily health can
benefit from fresh and fine air. Second, it is a serious flaw that because
these sessions are private sessions, no conversation takes place in them
except for backbiting, complaint, and nonsense of this kind, as opposed
to coffeehouses, where, because of the public gathering, one cannot find
occasion for things of this kind. I always sat with friends in coffeehouses
in the evening in Constantinople and Egypt, but I never heard discussions
of this kind. No discussion except for joking and jest took place there, nor
could it have taken place.
Examples of European and Asian Civilization. One great special quality
of Constantinople is that if someone wishes to view an image of European
and Asian civilization in a single folio, then he should see this place. Tour
the shops of booksellers, and on one side is an extremely large shop. There
is a floor of marble stone. There are extremely beautiful glass cabinets. All
the books are bound, and the bindings are not ordinary, but rather gener-
ally gilt and gilded. The owner of the shop is seated, having set up a table
and chairs. Two or three young, well-dressed boys are busy at work, mov-
ing this way and that. You set foot in the store. A boy brings a chair and
sets it in front of you, and hands you the catalogue of books. The price is
mentioned in the catalogue, and bargaining for more or less is not permit-
ted. [38]
On the other side, a disorderly pile of books is set on platforms on the
side of the street. The carpet for seating is laid out on the floor, and it, too,
is so small that there is not space for more than four people. A period of
some hours is required to settle on a price.
Similarly, shops of both types, of every profession and industry,
are found. The same is true of public cleanliness and elegance. Look at
Ghalaṭah, and it seems like a piece of Europe. Stores: tall, appointed, and
decorated. Streets: broad and even. There is no sign of dirt or filth any-
where. By contrast, in Istanbul, where the population is largely comprised
of Muslims, most streets are unclean and in some places so uneven that it
is difficult to walk.

Constantinople 45
Reason for the Difference in Conditions. Having come to this city, the
first thought that will come to the heart of a traveler will probably concern
why there is such a difference between the two parts of this glorious capital.
Thus, this thought came to my heart at first. I discussed and researched this
a great deal. I easily came to know the reason for the difference in the con-
ditions of the residents. That is, the poverty of the Muslims and the wealth
of other nations. But ostensibly this could not be considered the reason for
the filth and unevenness of the streets and thoroughfares. Thus, I inquired
of an esteemed Turkish officer, Ḥusain Ḥasīb Āfandī, police commis-
sioner.9 He said, “Our municipal taxes are very low. A great many things
are exempt from tax collection, but in Ghalaṭah, the European merchants
pay high taxes of their own accord. [39] Thus, the municipality can spend
those amounts generously.” I thought, “This is the same Ghalaṭah regarding
which Ibn-i Baṭūṭah has harshly complained of dirtiness and filth. Now
they have such care for cleanliness and tidiness that they pay large taxes
for it.” The fact is that cleanliness and propriety have become the leaven of
Europe these days.
The Form of the Buildings and Fire. The buildings here are of a form
completely different from the buildings of Hindustan. Houses are usually
of three or four stories. There is absolutely no courtyard. All the buildings
are made of wood. The homes of major amīrs and pāshās, too, are made
of wood, and this is the reason that fire often breaks out here. No month,
rather, no week passes without two or three homes burning to ruin, and
sometimes entire neighborhoods are burnt to ashes. Extreme care has been
taken and arrangements made by the sulṭān for extinguishing fires. Sev-
eral hundred people are appointed especially for this work. An extremely
tall tower has been built on which several workers are present at all times,
so when they see fire breaking out somewhere, they immediately sound
the alarm. Other small towers of this kind have been set up all around.
When fire breaks out somewhere, canons are immediately fired, and fire-
extinguishing workers from every part of the city arrive at the site with all
their instruments. They have been ordered to continue rushing headlong,
so much so that if someone walking down the street is crushed by their

46 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
onrush, there is no criminal accusation. I asked people why the buildings
were not made of stone and learned that they are quite uncomfortable in
the wintertime, and bodily health suffers. [40]
Climate. The climate here is extremely excellent. It is extremely cold in the
winter, and sometimes it even snows. The warm season, which I experi-
enced myself, is so pleasant that it cannot be described. It is a wonder why
the amīrs of our area do not travel to Constantinople instead of Shimlā
and Nainītāl.10 The water comes from the mountains and is extremely
agreeable and conducive to digestion.
Fruits. Fruits of every kind are in abundance, and the grapes and melons
in particular are incomparable. The melons of Lucknow are perhaps a bit
ahead in delicacy, but they cannot equal the melons of this place in sweet-
ness. Guavas, which the Arabs call injās [pear],11 are of a strange conical
shape, similar to carrots, not in color, but in form. But they are extremely
sweet and delicious. The apples are bigger and sweeter than the apples of
Kabul. There is a fruit here they call mishmish [apricot].12 It is somewhat
similar to the jāmun of our area.13 Fruits of every kind are extremely inex-
pensive. Grapes are at most two annas per seer. Apples, the best of the best,
two for a paisa. And so on.
Dress and Fashion. The dress and fashion is entirely European. From
outward appearance, it cannot be known if a person is Muslim or Chris-
tian. Christians and Jews all wear a red cap, which could have been the
distinguishing dress of the Turks, and for this reason there is no means
of distinguishing between the nations. In one respect this practice is
good because the more the traces of difference among different nations
are eliminated, the more beneficial it is for civilization. But in matters of
social necessity, it leads to serious problems. [41] I often faced difficulties
because of it, and I always thought that if Ḥaz¨rat ‘Umar gave the order to
the Christians to restrict themselves to national clothing, he was right to
do so. The astonishing thing is that the religious group here, meaning the
‘ulamā and teachers, too, could not escape the effect of Europe. There are
buttons on their pajamas, like pants. The only difference is that they are

Constantinople 47
wide and loose on top and are beautifully pleated. Instead of a kurta or
achkan, there is only a wāyiskōt ˙ [waistcoat]. They wear a robe on top of
the waistcoat, and this is the distinguishing symbol that separates them
from other groups of people. The influence of Europe is also found in the
fact that they do not fasten the buttons of their robes, and the waistcoat
remains open from the front. These people, too, generally use the Turk-
ish cap, but a band of white fabric is wrapped around it, which they call a
laffah in Arabic, and it is considered the special symbol of the scholars. I
shall write details of women’s clothing in the discussion of women’s cul-
ture and society.
Congregational Mosques and Royal Palaces. The excellent buildings
and monumental buildings of this place are the congregational masjids
and royal palaces. Discussion of the congregational masjids, with some
degree of detail, will come later under a separate heading. They call royal
palaces here sarāe [serai]. Their number is twenty or twenty-one, and
all are located at far-off distances. These buildings are from the time of
different sulṭāns and are buildings of extreme grandeur and glory. One
palace, which is made of marble from top to bottom, is right on the edge
of the sea and is extremely large, lofty, and beautiful. When the emperor
of Germany was recently a guest of the sulṭān, this is the palace in which
he stayed.
No Town Hall. It is a matter of great wonder that in the entire city there is
no town hall. Even the public garden, meaning [42] the bāgh-i ‘āmah, is so
small that it does not befit this magnificent capital.
Courts. The courts (except for one or two) are all located in one place,
and they call this collective building the Bāb-i ‘Ālī. The office of the prime
minister is also here. These buildings are not so magnificent. The High
Court, which they call the Maḥkamat al-tam’īz here, is at a distance
from the Bāb-i ‘Ālī. Although I did not go inside it, from the outside it
seems like a very glorious building. The court of the police commissioner
is in Ghalaṭah. I toured it well. The building is not so remarkable, but it is
extremely orderly and well appointed. A very valuable Turkish carpet is

48 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
spread out in the assembly room. The chairs, too, are extremely beautiful
and elegant. I also saw the office of Ma‘ārif, meaning the Department of
Education. It is an ordinary building, but due to cleanliness and orderli-
ness, it seems attractive.
The Progress of Education in Colleges and Schools
Education. If I could have had any other purpose in this distant journey
apart from visiting libraries, then it was to gain an estimate of the style
of education and progress of education here. Thus, I paid more attention
to it than to all other matters, and, to the extent that I could, I spared no
effort. However, readers should not expect that I was also entirely success-
ful in my objectives and that my educational report will be a complete
report. The efforts that I was able to make for inquiries were that I went
to the office of the Department of Education several times, inquired after
matters requiring investigation from the officers of education, [43] went
and saw large, important colleges and schools myself, met teachers and
professors, and obtained the yearly reports of the colleges. But even with
all these efforts, one cannot achieve complete success here. It is a strange
practice among the Turks that they look at every single thing from the
perspective of politics, and for this reason they do not like for any matter
of business to come onto the public scene. The report of the Department of
Education that is published with the annual record is extremely brief and
purely summary. So much so that the salaries of the professors and teach-
ers are not even mentioned. The reports of some colleges, for example the
Maktab-i Ḥarbiyah [Military College] and the Maktab-i Sulṭānī [Imperial
College], are published separately, but there is nothing in them except the
results of the examinations and the curriculum of instruction.14
At first, I thought that I had few means of access, and this was why
I could learn very little information, but when I read the book by Khair
al-Dīn Pāshā, wazīr of Ṭūnis, I was consoled.15 Where he has discussed
Turkey and has written the state of its civilizational and educational prog-
ress, he has employed extreme cursoriness, and has apologized, saying,
“The information about Turkey that I have written, I have written by
means of English books, and for this reason could not write in detail. But

Constantinople 49
not even this much can be found in the writings of Muslims.” After this
preface and apology, I begin my principle purpose.
Different Methods of Education. Classical Education. Modern Educa-
tion. In Constantinople, rather, in all the Islamic regions, there are two
methods of education: classical and modern. Classical education began
with Turkish rule. Thus, Urkhān (died 761 Hijrī) [1359–60], who was the
second emperor in this line, established a madrasa in Iznīq [İznik], and
this was the first madrasa that was established in the Ottoman regions.16
After Urkhān, other sulṭāns attended to education with royal ambition and
established hundreds of academies and madrasas. [44] Thus, in my trea-
tise, Gużishtah ta‘līm, a full, detailed account of this can be found.17 The
history of new education begins from the time when Turkish government,
having left the Asian mold, entered the European mold. The founder of
this revolution was Sulṭān Maḥmūd, who first adopted European fashion
and equipped his army in the manner of Europe.18 This same modernizer19
laid the foundation of the Military College in 1250 Hijrī [1834–35],20 which
was the first college of modern education. This college still exists and is
the center of all military madrasas. After Sulṭān Maḥmūd, in 1261 Hijrī
[1845–46], Sulṭān ‘Abd al-Majīd21 further extended modern education and
established the rushdiyah schools.22 Since then, this education has con-
tinued extensively and is making progress daily. Four levels of modern
education have been established.
Elementary Education. Ibtidā’iyah [elementary]. Its duration is at most
five years, but an intelligent and astute student can progress having fin-
ished it in two or three years, rather, in just a year or two. In it, instruc-
tion is given in the Glorious Quran, the Turkish language, Arabic spelling,
script, and arithmetic up to long division.
Rushdiyah [Secondary Schools]. Duration of education: three years.
Instruction is given in Turkish dictation, elements of the Turkish lan-
guage, Turkish syntax, the tenets of Islam in the Turkish language, all four
parts of arithmetic, French, Arabic, geography, geometry, the principles

50 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
of commercial bookkeeping, and cartography. This level is approximately
equal to the “middle” of our area, or somewhat ahead of it.23
I‘dādiyah [High Schools] and the Number of Its Students. After rush-
diyah is i‘dādiyah, which can be called “entrance.” In 1892, the collective
number of students of this class was 5,215. This includes the madrasas of
all districts as well as the capital itself.24 [45]
After i‘dādiyah are different specialized colleges, for example, the Civil
College, the Legal College, and so on, a detailed description of which will
come later.25 The number of general and specialized madrasas of every kind
in Constantinople is five hundred,* among which thirteen are major colleges.
The Progress of Education in the Era of the Present Sulṭān. The Annual
Expenses of Education. It is generally accepted that education has made
extreme progress in the time of the present sulṭān, and continues to do so
daily. At the time of the sulṭān’s enthronement, the number of rushdiyah
madrasas was 96, but now it is 405. The number of new madrasas of every
kind that have been founded in the fifteen-year reign of the sulṭān is two
thousand. Along with that, the number of students in schools and colleges
continues to grow so much that the educational progress report of the pre-
ceding year has no relation to the report of the succeeding year. In the
lecture on the general progress of the Turks that Professor Vámbéry gave
several years ago, the number of students at the Maktab al-Ḥuqūq [Legal
College] was reported as three hundred. But when I was in Constantinople,
there were 1,200 students present in this college. During my stay in Egypt,
I read in Cairo’s famous newspaper al-Muwayyad that “When the present
sulṭān took the reins of the government in hand, the expenses in education
were three lakh pounds annually.26 But now they are eight lakh pounds
annually.” This amount is equivalent to one crore twenty lakh of our region.
Inviting Students. In truth, the sulṭān has a strange and wondrous attach-
ment to education. The Civil College and the Legal College, which are the
*
from Qāmūs al-Islām [This footnote first appears in the second edition.]

Constantinople 51
renowned colleges of Constantinople, were established by the sulṭān him-
self. [46] The lauded gentleman has such regard for these colleges that he
has come to inspect them in person several times. During the time that I
was in Constantinople, the lauded gentleman invited the students of all the
major colleges to a royal banquet. Kāghaż-khānah [Kağıthane] is a famous
place to visit in Constantinople where once a week there is a gathering of
spectators.27 This place was suggested and selected for the banquet and the
order was given that the students of each college be called there in turn.
First the Military College, then the Civil College (Civil Service College)
and the students of other colleges were invited. As the students walked
from the college, a royal band played in front of them in accordance with
the order of the sulṭān. Because the sulṭān himself could not participate in
these assemblies by reason of state considerations, a wazīr always partici-
pated in the banquet on his behalf and conveyed the salaam of the sulṭān
to the students. At that time, the students would cry out bādshāhim choq
yashā (meaning may our emperor live for a very long time) with great pas-
sion and sincerity of feeling.28
In the branch of education, an extremely beneficial invention that
recently took place at the special suggestion of the sulṭān is the found-
ing of the Maktab al-‘Ashāyir [Tribal College].29 Although at this time
education is progressing in all the Ottoman regions, up to now, the tribes
of Arabia were nearly entirely deprived of this beneficence, the reason
for which was their own heedlessness and bedouin quality. The sulṭān
gave the order to found a college especially for the Arab tribes and, along
with it, a large and well-ordered boarding house. During the time of my
stay, farmans were issued in the name of rulers and governors that boys
from the esteemed tribes of Arabs in Ḥijāz [Hejaz], Yaman [Yemen],
Diyarbakr [Diyarbakır], Baṣrah [Basra], Baghdād [Baghdād], Ṭarābulus
al-Gharb [Tripoli], Ḥalab [Aleppo], Mauṣil [Mosul], and Shām [Syria], be
selected and sent. [47] The sulṭān approved that their expenses of every
kind be paid by the government. On 12 Rabī‘ al-Awwal 1310 [October 4,
1892], it was opened with great glory and magnificence and inaugural
ceremonies were performed. One cannot find the equal of such an out-
standing effort for the training and cultural refinement of the Arabs in
all Islamic history.

52 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
The Dār al-Shafaqah Madrasa. Even more proof of royal generosity is
to be found in the Dār al-Shafaqah [Darüşşafaka], which has been estab-
lished especially for orphans.30 One thousand orphans receive education
in this madrasa, and all of them are boarders. The burden of the food,
clothing, and all other necessary expenses of this enormous group does
not fall on the Department of Education, but rather on the Great Sulṭān
himself.
Major Colleges and Schools. Among the colleges and schools, the ones
that are most worthy of mention are these:
The Royal Military College
The Imperial College
The Civil College
The Legal College,
meaning College of Law
The Engineering College The Language College I saw these colleges myself and have
obtained detailed information regarding
their method of education, and so on. For
this reason, I shall include them under a
separate heading later.
The following subjects are taught at this
college: fiqh; principles of fiqh; Roman law;
law of commerce; principles of trial; pun-
ishments; maritime law; political economy,
meaning the politics of cities; the laws of
the sultanates of Europe; briefly, the history
of the creation of law and its developments,
period by period. [48] The total number
of students is 1,200, among whom 600 are
boarders. Those educated here can become
a munṣif and a ṣadr al-ṣudūr.
31 The period
of instruction is four years.
The period of education is six years. This is
similar to Roorkee College.32
German, French, Greek, Armenian, Latin,
Italian, and Russian languages are taught
in it.

The College of Industries,
meaning technical school
Deputy College Maritime College Agricultural College Constantinople 53
The yearly expense is 8,250 pounds, that
is, 123,750 rupees. The number of stu-
dents is 240 and all are orphan boys.
Their expenses are paid by the fund of the
madrasah itself. Up to now, blacksmith-
ing and carpentry were taught in it, but in
the past year the secretary of the madrasa,
Taufīq Bey Āfandī, requested that the work
of machines be taught.
This college has been established on ex-
tremely excellent principles. In the previous
period, it was not stipulated for the muftīs
and qāz¨īs who were appointed to pass a
test in a particular course of instruction of
any kind. Now the rule has been set that a
person who is not educated at this college
cannot be appointed to shar‘ī [Islamic legal]
posts. This method [49] has completely
obstructed the path to appointments by rec-
ommendation. Education in fiqh takes place
at an extremely high level at this college.
Several things of modern education, too,
have been added to bring about familiarity
with the necessities of the present age.
Education in navigation takes place here.
.. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. .. ..
Noteworthy Matters Related to the System of Education
A few points related to the method of education are especially noteworthy.
(1) The Compulsoriness of French. That in nearly all colleges and schools,
French is compulsory, the result of which is that one cannot find even

54 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
an ordinary person educated in modern learning who is unfamiliar with
French.
(2) Education in Science and the Arts. In all major colleges, education in
physics, chemistry, geology, and so on, is compulsory, and practical exer-
cise is given in these sciences. The instruments of these subjects are avail-
able in abundance in every college for this purpose.
(3) Education of the Highest Order in History. Education in history is
of the highest order. I saw the course of the Civil College. It is in six thick
volumes, in which, in addition to other regions, there is a detailed history
of Europe in addition to other countries. Along with that, the great virtue
is that it contains discussion and refutation of the errors about Islamic his-
tory that many authors of Europe have made.
(4) Education in All Modern Sciences Takes Place through the Turkish
Language. Apart from the Imperial College, in which Christian students
are in abundance, in all other remaining madrasas, [50] arts and sciences
of every kind are taught in the regional language, meaning Turkish. All
modern sciences have been translated into Turkish and continue to be so
from time to time. Although it is debatable whether or not translation is a
superior means of education, and the great renowned theorists of Hindu-
stan have taken the negative position in this debate, the debate is probably
particular to Hindustan, where the regional language is not the language
of governance. The Turkish language is the language of the sultanate, and
in the entire world one cannot find an example of a sultanate that has
progressed having acquired arts and sciences in the language of another
nation. The progress of England began at a time when the arts and sci-
ences were transferred into English from Latin, and there is no doubt that
if Turkey’s progress, too, is possible, then it can only happen by means of
the regional language.
(5) The System of Boarding. The thing that is most valuable and respect-
able in the matter of education and training is the boarding system. The
reality is that Turkey can claim with extreme pride that there can be no

Constantinople 55
better system of boarding than the one that it has adopted. There are
boarding houses attached to all the major colleges, and a great many stu-
dents live in them, but the rule is observed that food, clothing, fashion, liv-
ing space, and appointments should all be uniform, and that there should
be no suspicion of differences in rank in the condition of the students. The
cost of clothing is taken along with the rent for boarding and the fees for
food, and the clothes of the students are prepared by the college itself. All
the students eat at tables and chairs, and extreme care is taken for good
manners, cleanliness, and ceremony in all things. The amount of fees is
no less than five pounds per year in any college, [51] and in the Imperial
College it is forty pounds, meaning six hundred rupees.
It is the wondrous estimable generosity of the Turks that despite the
excessiveness of the fees, the poor are not deprived of the benefit of these
colleges. In every college, there is a considerable number of poor students.
So much assistance is given to them on behalf of wealthy Turks that they
can pay all the expenses of the college. At the Imperial College, the fees for
which are forty pounds per year, two hundred students are poor and less
fortunate. Among them, amīrs and members of the government pay the
fees of 150 students, and the sulṭān himself bestows those of fifty from his
own pocket. The effect of this is that on the grounds of the college no one
can distinguish in any way that such-and-such a student is poor and less
fortunate. The uniformity of the students produces an extremely powerful
idea of unity and nationhood among them, and for the poor, obtaining the
society of the upper class produces in them the material of ambitiousness
and high aspiration. In the major colleges of Europe, there is the great
shortcoming that less fortunate people do not receive much benefit from
their munificence. The Turks have taken measures to redress and guard
against this loss, and have done so extremely nicely.
Seeing this manner of boarding, I would recall my own academy and
would mourn the different ranks in its boarding house. But my lament
was in fact not at the state of the college, but rather at those greats of the
nation to whom God has given wealth and fortune but not the guidance to
endeavor, by means of their own generosity, that in our educational insti-
tutions, the poor and the powerful appear at the same high level. I hereby
declare that the thing that is most necessary, [52] and extremely necessary,

56 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
in our national college is that the dress, fashion, food, living space, and
furniture of all the students be made entirely one and the same, and that
the different strata that remain in the college today be completely erased.
If not, then there is no soul of nationhood in the college.
Student Dress. There is another novelty in the colleges and schools here,
and it is extremely beneficial and effective. It is that on the collar of the
coat of every student, the name of the college in which he is being edu-
cated is embroidered in golden thread. The letters of the silken thread are
raised and of the highest order in accordance with the Naskh script. If you
go to the thoroughfares of the colleges and schools at around four o’clock,
a wondrous, enchanting sight appears. Whole crowds of students emerge
from the madrasas, divide into numerous ranks, and walk with such order
and regulation that one might say a regulated army is marching. The rosy,
pale complexion of the boys, the black coat over it, and the golden mono-
gram of the college on the collar of the coats seems so attractive that it is
beyond description.
In addition to decoration and adornment, grandeur and majesty, a
great benefit from this practice is that when the students step out into
the market for recreation, they cannot engage in any inappropriate behav-
ior. The dress of the college, which is compulsory to be worn at all times,
causes one to recognize that they are students. Thus, they have no choice
but to be mindful of the reputation of the college. Furthermore, if some
boy participates in some disagreeable company or is guilty of any inde-
cency, a policeman will grab him and bring him to the school or college
where he is educated.
Many Students Living in Each Room. There appears to be one defect in
the boarding system here, and it is that there are not separate rooms; [53]
instead, there is one large hall for fifty or sixty boys in which beds are laid
out according to their number. At the headboard of each bed is a small
cabinet, which holds ordinary clothing and books. When I initially saw the
boarding houses here, on the whole the thought of their contemptibleness
occurred to me, especially because the ceremonious and well-appointed

Constantinople 57
rooms of the academy were before my eyes. But with further research, I
learned that this method is not devoid of benefit. Although there is no
doubt that the principle reason for this deficiency is the abundance of the
population and the unavailability of sufficient land, with respect to the
benefits that cannot be obtained without this particular method, it would
not be inappropriate to claim that such had been done intentionally and
such alone was appropriate.
The Uniformity of the Social Life of All Boarders. The extremely ben-
eficial use that has been made of this method is that the daily life of all
boarders has been fixed upon uniform principles. For example, as dawn
breaks, the watchmen, who walk around the sleeping rooms all night,
awaken the boarders. Spouts have been attached to the wall in accordance
with the number of boys, and beneath them a small watercourse has been
made. All the boys went and sat together there. There is such commitment
to the boys’ arriving together that in some colleges there is a machine
that turns to open the mouths of all the spouts together. When all the
boys arrive, a servant turns the machine, and, when the allotted time has
passed, closes it. If any boy comes late, he will have to turn back because a
great deal of water cannot be wasted for just one person. Having washed
their hands and faces, [54] all the boys go and sit on benches in the read-
ing room (which is reserved for reading books, and where a supervising
instructor remains present), and occupy themselves by memorizing les-
sons or studying their readings. All the students get up together and go
into the dining room. After the meal, the school bell rings, and everyone
goes and sits in the college rooms. At night, too, all the students read in
a single room (reading room) and, when it is time to sleep, all stand up
together and move into the sleeping room. In sum—arising from sleep,
washing hands and face, studying lessons, eating, performing namāz, and
at ten o’clock at night, each going and lying in his respective bed—the stu-
dents are required do all these tasks together. By this method, maintain a
schedule becomes a habit, and, gradually, it becomes second nature. For
this method, it is necessary to arrange for the fifty to sixty boys to live
in a single room. Otherwise, arrangement for all tasks to be performed

58 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
together cannot be made in separate rooms. Our college, Ẓaḥūr Ḥusain
˙
Wārd
, which was just recently established, has been established on this
principle.33
A Few Things Are Still Lacking in the Progress of Education. Concern-
ing the breadth and progress of education, although such care has been
taken, because the new method of education has only recently been put
into effect, there is a lack of a great many things, which, it is hoped, will
gradually be fulfilled. Among them the fact that there is no debating club
or intellectual-scientific society in any college, rather, in the entire city.
For this reason, the students do not have the opportunity to develop abili-
ties in public speaking. As a result, those who have obtained degrees from
these colleges cannot give a lecture or speech on any topic in a public gath-
ering. The effect of this is also that in the educated group, the liveliness,
freethinking, ambitiousness, and high-mindedness that are the requisites
of the new education have not been produced. [55]
One very great defect is that the existence of large colleges and schools
is limited to the walls of the seat of the caliphate. Although in large cit-
ies madrasas have been established in abundance, they are generally ele-
mentary or rushdiyah, meaning madrasas of the middle grade. As far as I
am aware, in Beirut, Damascus, Aleppo, and Jerusalem there is not even
one intellectual-scientific madrasa to which the word college can truly be
applied.
Even greater is the regret that all the colleges and academies of Con-
stantinople that I mentioned are paid for by the government. The nation
has not yet given this any attention. That is, in such a large capital of the
sultanate, there is not even one national college. No government, no mat-
ter how powerful and wealthy it is, can be the guarantor of the intellec-
tual-scientific needs of the entire country. And even if it were, it is not
very beneficial. The mental and spiritual powers of a nation whose every
need the government fulfills become dead and useless. To the magnificent
intellectual workshops spread throughout Europe, the nation has contrib-
uted the largest share. The famous universities of England, Cambridge and
Oxford, were founded by national efforts alone, and to this day they have
not seen fit to bear the burden of government favor.

Constantinople 59
After this summary report, we write the detailed circumstances of
several colleges.
Military College [Maktab-i Ḥarbiyah]
This is a very large college, rather, it is a very large university, of which
the Turks are proud, and, in truth, it is deserving of this pride. Although
military education is to some extent detached from the sense of technical
education, and in this regard [56] it was apparently not befitting to men-
tion the Military College under the heading of “Progress of Education,”
still, instruction in physics, chemistry, mathematics, and all the branches
of medicine especially, in addition to the military sciences, is given to
such an extent in this college that we cannot call it outside the sphere of
technical education. Sulṭān Maḥmūd founded this college in 1250 Hijrī
[1834–35]. Relative to this time, a good deal of progress has taken place in
the building, and the curriculum of education has become so extensive
and superior that one might say it has ceased to be a college at all.
The number of military madrasas subordinate to this college is 37,
among which 18 are i‘dādiyah and 27 are rushdiyah, in which a total of
9,224 students are acquiring an education.
Details will be learned from the following chart:
Type of madrasaMadrasas in the capitalMadrasas in the districts
Boarder Non-boarder Boarder Non-boarder
A‘dādī 1069 0 745 0
Rushdiyah 155 2,425 128 2,225
This college (the Military College) is a college of great magnificence
and glory. Although the general rule in Constantinople is that no person
can be admitted onto the grounds of a madrasa without the permission
of the secretary of the madrasa, there are even more checks and controls
at this madrasa. When I attempted to visit it, people said that the irādah-i
sunnah,
34 meaning the permission of the sulṭān himself, was necessary.
[57] Although ‘Us˙mān Pāshā,35 in whose service I had already had the
honor of appearing at the time, could easily have had permission granted

60 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
to me, I did not think it appropriate to trouble him for this undertak-
ing. I was on informal terms with Ḥusain Ḥasīb Āfandī, the police com-
missioner. I spoke about it with him. He said, “Dar Ḥarbiyah māżūn
nīstam.”36 Left with no other choice, I had to rely on my own effort. I had
already learned that the secretary of the Military College was Żakī Pāshā,
who is an extremely capable and highly educated person. I thought that I
should meet him myself without any mediation. Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān, too,
was of the same opinion. Thus, we both went to the home of the afore-
mentioned pāshā.
Meeting Żakī Pāshā to Visit the Military College. As it happened, he
had gone out. The person said, “Please, just wait a short while, he may
come back soon.” Meanwhile, he arrived. He turned to face us as he
stepped out of the carriage. Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān and I were both in Arab
dress. Although there was a silken turban on my head and a golden band
around my waist, because of my qafṭān and my robe, I appeared by my
overall appearance to be an Arab. The aforementioned pāshā was in an
extreme hurry at the time. As soon as he said “Salām ‘alaik,” he thrust
his hand into his pocket and took out some majīdīs (Turkish coin). First
I was severely shocked. Then I thought, “Na‘ūż billāh! He thinks we are
beggars, like common Arabs!” With that thought I became extremely irri-
tated, and along with the irritation, angered, too. I shouted, “Shū hāżā?
Mā jīnā li-hāżā. Lisnā min al-fuqarā’!”37 meaning, “What is this? We have
not come for this! We are not faqīrs!” Although the pāshā did not under-
stand Arabic, he understood from the look on my face and the tone of
my words that the action had offended me. [58] He turned his attention
to Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān. “Why is he in a rage? And what does he want?”
Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān was able to speak some broken Turkish. He described
the purpose and aim of my visit. The pāshā became extremely embar-
rassed. Along with apologies, he said, “Please, go to the upper gallery. I
will come in a little while.” There were some esteemed officers gathered
on the upper gallery. They welcomed us with extreme reverence. Coffee
came as usual. Each person was greeted in turn. When they learned that I
was a resident of Hindustan and had come here for the purpose of scien-
tific research, they became so enthralled that interest and affection were

Constantinople 61
expressed by their every word and gesture. It was extremely unfortunate
that I understood neither Turkish nor French and they could not converse
in any other language. One by one, they came and sat near me, and, along
with expressing affection, expressed regret that “We do not understand
your language.” After a little while, Żakī Pāshā sent word asking extremely
politely to be excused: “I have crucial business to attend to, so I cannot
come myself; but I have ordered an officer to take you on a thorough tour
of the college.” The name of that gentleman was Raz¨ā Bey, and he had the
rank of mīr-alāī [miralay].38 The pāshā’s asking to be excused could not
have been based on pretense. Indeed, a great many departments really are
entrusted to him, and his entire day is spent making rounds. Still, there is
no doubt that he felt extremely embarrassed by his behavior and this, too,
was one reason for his not coming.
In learning that when ‘ulamā and Sūfīs meet some amīr or officer of
rank here, [59] they do so with the purpose of getting their hands on some
shiny coins, my irritation with Żakī Pāshā’s negative suspicion went away,
but I felt great anguish at the condition of this group. I used to think that
the practice of begging for offerings and oblations was exclusive to Hindu-
stan, but, alas, there is no escape from it here, either.
Going to the Boys’ Dining Room. The Cleanliness and Fine Manners
of the Boys While Eating. To make a long story short, we went to the
Military College with Raz¨ā Bey. There was a guard at the gate. The sol-
diers saluted us according to military custom. When we entered, it was not
just a college, but a proper colony. Raz¨ā Bey first took us into his private
room. A few other officers of the college were present there. We were intro-
duced to them. As usual, coffee came. After a little while, Raz¨ā Bey said,
“The dining bell has already rung. Come, before anything else, let me take
you on a tour of the dining room.” Because at that time the d ˙
ā’ining rūm
(dining room) and the buildings attached to it had been demolished and
were being rebuilt anew, a building at some distance from the row of col-
lege buildings had been temporarily set up, and a clean and level road had
been prepared from the college to the building. When the boys emerged
from their rooms and headed toward the dining hall, a wondrous, heart-
enchanting scene appeared before the eyes. There were thirty or forty lines

62 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
of five or six boys each, and they were going along with such order and
regularity that you might say a regulated army was marching. Their fash-
ion and dress was entirely uniform, and because all the boys were Turks
or Syrian Arabs, there was not much difference in their complexion and
appearance. The astonishing thing is that although no officer was with the
group, nor did they know about our coming, not a single movement of
theirs was opposed to order and arrangement, and there was absolutely no
sign of noise and shouting. When we entered the room, all the boys were
already seated at the table. The hall was extremely large and beautiful, and
there was gilt ornamentation on the ceiling. [60] There were foods of two
or three kinds and, in accordance with Turkish custom, one large dish
was set in the middle of each group of four boys. There were no forks or
knives. There were only spoons. But the boys ate with such fine manners
that neither did their hands become soiled nor could a stain have appeared
anywhere on the tablecloth. The boys are probably held to strict standards
of cleanliness. It seemed as if the four or five hundred boys who were pres-
ent in the hall had changed their clothes just before coming. Wherever we
passed, the boys would stand up and say, “Tafaz¨z¨al yā maulānā.”39 At their
insistence, I ate a few bites. The food was not bad. But I was looking for
Hindustani qormah. Where was that to be found here?
Having left the dining room, we strolled around for a little while until
the college bell rang and the boys moved into the lecture room.
Lecture Rooms. The lecture rooms (rooms of instruction) are not of the
same form as those of our Hindustan. Stretching into the distance in a
straight line are a great many rooms whose form is like that of common
buildings. The professor sits on a high platform. There was even a wooden
railing around some platforms. Whichever room Raz¨ā Bey (and we along
with him) entered, a boy would stand up and say the word baq with a loud
cry.40 With that cry, all the boys would stand up and greet us with a gesture
of the hand. I learned that whenever an officer of the college comes, the
boys show him respect in this way. Raz¨ā Bey introduced us to all the pro-
fessors, but unfortunately we could not understand anyone’s language. [61]
The hammam, printing house, draftsman house, and a great many
buildings of this kind that are on the grounds of the college—we toured

Constantinople 63
them all. There are so many of these buildings that we walked around
continuously for nearly two hours before no more remained. The room
for instruction in anatomy is extremely large and the implements for ana-
tomical procedures have been collected in abundance. I had never seen
examples of cartography and drawing like the ones that I saw here. The
innovation that I saw in the printing house was that maps of geography
were printed having been made on stone instead of paper. The map that
was being prepared at the time was extremely dense and fine, and in truth
was work of painstaking detail.
The Moral Character of the Professors. For the amusement of the stu-
dents, there is a beautiful pond in which fish of different colors live, and
benches and chairs are set up all around. For professors and teachers,
there is a separate pond a short distance away. Because we had become
tired while walking, we took a breather there, and kept company for a
while. Rajab Āfandī, who is appointed to teach Turkish composition and
knows Persian, joined us on the final tour. I could speak with the esteemed
officers of the college through him without any trouble. I cannot describe
the quality of the kind manners and Islamic affection with which the pro-
fessors and students treated me. It was extremely regrettable that the day
on which I saw the college was not a day of practical instruction. For this
reason, military exercises, that is, drills, marksmanship, horsemanship,
preparing trenches, preparing temporary fortifications—we could not see
anything of this kind. We could have gone to see them on some other day,
but the college was so far from our residence that [62] we could not find
the nerve again.
Numerous Branches of Instruction. There are numerous branches of
instruction at this college.
(1) Military Officers. Military Officers. This is the highest level, and its
duration of study is three years. It has two branches, technical [fannī] and
military [‘askarī]. In the technical, the following subjects are taught: land
division and cosmography; optics; machines; architecture; the French, Ger-
man, and Russian languages; the besiegement of fortresses and principles

64 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
of battle; military telegraph; posts, salaries, and pensions of the military
officers; military inventions; practical studies; forms of architecture; the
roads of the Ottoman territories and the railway lines of all the territories
of Europe; the art of heavy weaponry; the science of geology; the organiza-
tion and principles of the militaries of Europe; the famous battles of the
world and the causes of victory and defeat and the details their occurrence
with respect to military principles; geometry; algebra; palūghrāfiyā;41 the
art of light weaponry; writing; the history of the art of war; drawing.
Most of the same subjects are also taught in the military42 branch.
Along with this, there are also several modern subjects. Basic instruction
in most of the subjects that are taught at both of these levels has already
taken place in the rushdiyah and i‘dādiyah. At these levels, they are merely
completed, and this is the reason that so many different subjects can be
acquired in three years. From the rushdiyah to this level, the total period
of education is ten years.
(2) Cavalry. Education in Cavalry. Its duration of instruction is three years,
and, in addition to practical exercises, instruction is given in the following
subjects: traditional geometry; theoretical and practical palūghrāfiyā; the
French, German, and Russian languages; [63] chemistry; the art of weap-
onry; military inventions; and military geography.
(3) Infantry. Duration of education, three years. In this, in addition to
practical exercises, there is education in military geography; the art of
weaponry; German, French, and Russian languages; military inventions;
light fortifications; and health care.
(4) Baiṭārī, Meaning the Medical Treatment of Animals. Baiṭārī, mean-
ing animal medicine. Period of education, four years. Subjects of instruc-
tion: common diseases; the art of birth; the art of equestrianism; internal
diseases; inborn diseases; the art of surgery; external diseases; the French
language; writing; organic chemistry; uncompounded medicine; dissection
and anatomy, physiology; botany; biology; inorganic chemistry; and the
science of geology, mineralogy, and mining. In all four of these divisions,
nearly six hundred students are under instruction, and after obtaining

Constantinople 65
certificates, they are given official posts as per rankings. Beneath them are
the classes of i‘dādiyah and rushdiyah, whose total period of instruction
is seven years, and instruction is given in history, geography, arithmetic
and accounting, geometry, machine work, and subjects of this kind. All
together, the students who acquire an education in the different branches of
this college are 1,500 in number, among whom 1,000 are boarders.
The Number of Professors and Teachers. The professors, assistant profes-
sors, and teachers are eighty-seven, among whom most reside right on the
premises of the college. Most of the professors are educated at the highest
level and are esteemed officers. Among them, six people hold the rank of
pāshā, whose names are S ˙arwat Pāshā, secretary; Fāyiq Pāshā, professor of
organic chemistry; Hizbar Pāshā, professor of cavalry education; Tafaw-
wuq Pāshā, professor of geology; Shākir Pāshā, professor of the elements
of war; and ‘Us˙mān Pāshā, professor of German. [64] Nine professors have
obtained the rank of mīr-ālāī.
Imperial College [Maktab-i Sulṭānī]
This, too, is an old college, and is more distinguished than all colleges
except the Military College.43 It is located in Ghalaṭah-sarāe [Galatasaray],
where European merchants mostly reside, and for this reason there are
more Christian boys in it than in all other colleges.
I regret that at the time that I saw this college, it was a time of holiday,
and apart from two or three officers, meaning the secretary and assistant
secretary, and so on, no other officer was present.44 The college building
is two stories. The boarding house and lecture rooms are all on the upper
level. There is an extremely large room for instruction in biology, in which
there are many dead animals of every kind and very large skeletons of
animals. I had never seen the skeleton of a whale before. For experiments
in chemistry and electricity, expensive instruments have been made abun-
dantly available.
I very much liked that an extremely large hall is furnished for ill board-
ers in which there are many beds, and so on, and numerous attendants are
present at all times. In this way, the doctor finds ease in diagnosing and

66 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
treating the boys, and he can see all the ill at the same time. Otherwise, if
there were separate rooms, then coming to see each ill person one at a time
and sufficiently visiting and making inquiries after each patient would be
seriously difficult.
The expense of this college is eighteen thousand pounds, meaning
two lakh, seventy thousand rupees annually, [65] but this also includes
the amount of the scholarships for poor students. The collective number
of students is eight hundred, of whom most are boarders. The room of the
sleeping quarters of the boarders is extremely large. It is magnificent and
of pleasant atmosphere. A summary of a few items from the regulations of
the boarding house is included below:
1.  The food, clothes, bedding, books, paper, pens, and so on, of all
boarders will be provided by the college.
2.  Forty pounds per year (six hundred rupees) will be taken as fees
from the boarder.
3.  Such students will also be admitted who can pay two-thirds or
one-third of the fees, or who cannot pay them at all, but their
number will be fixed, which will be determined at the beginning
of each year following an inquiry by the office of director of public
instruction. (One should remember that the remainder of the fees
of such students are paid by the sulṭān and the amīrs of the city,
and for this reason, with respect to food, dress, and furniture, and
so on, no difference of any kind between them and the fortunate
students can be sensed.)
4.  At the time of admission, 15 pounds, meaning 225 rupees, will be
taken from every student for the sake of clothing.
5.  The fees of students who do not stay in the boarding house at night
are twenty pounds per year and cannot be reduced under any
circumstances.
6.  The fees of nonboarders are ten pounds per year and cannot be
reduced under any circumstances. [66]
7.  Boarders shall receive permission to go home only once per week,
and when they come and go it is necessary for a trusted servant to
be with them.

Constantinople 67
8.  No boarder can keep more than ten qurush (one and one quarter
rupees) with him in one week.
With respect to education, the distinctive quality that is in this college
is that all the arts and sciences are taught in French, and for this reason
most of the professors are either French or German. Along with that, edu-
cation in the Turkish language is of an extremely high level. Education
in Arabic and Persian, too, is compulsory, though it is not at the highest
level. The remaining languages, Greek, Armenian, English, German, Ital-
ian, and Latin, are included in the curriculum, and many students study
them, too. But education in them is optional, not compulsory.
The subjects that are taught in Turkish, Persian, and Arabic, apart
from the literary sciences and the Glorious Quran are as follows: tenets,
fiqh, ethics, history of the Ottoman Empire, recitation of the Quran, and
hadith and Quranic exegesis. But education in recitation and hadith and
Quranic exegesis begin in the fourth year and take place only once per
week. French is taught from the very beginning and continues regularly
until the conclusion of instruction, meaning seven years. Along with syn-
tax, morphology, and literature, the principles of composition and the art
of rhetoric are taught up to the highest level, and the following subjects,
too, are taught by means of this language: arithmetic and accounting,
algebra, geography, geometry, chemistry, biology, physics, botany, [67]
electricity, acoustics, geology, engineering design, and imitative design.
The Number of Professors and Teachers. The total number of teachers
and professors is seventy-four, among whom twenty-six are German and
French, and the remainder are Turks.
The reality is that with respect to the extensiveness of the building, the
provision of intellectual-scientific instruments, the breadth of instruction,
and the excellence of administration, no college in all of Constantinople
is more excellent. Of course, it is regrettable that the people receiving edu-
cation in the high classes are mostly Christians. The number of Muslims
is very small. Shaikh ‘Abd al-Fattāḥ Āfandī kindly gave me the current
annual report of the results of examinations. In it, all the people who
passed examinations at the highest level are mostly Christian. I bear no

68 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
malice toward the progress of Christians. By God I do not. But I certainly
feel anguish at the decline of Muslims.
Civil College [Maktab-i Mulkiyah]
This college, which is the civil service college of this place, has been es-
tablished by the sulṭān himself, and the lauded gentleman pays special
attention to it. Thus, he has already twice graced it with his presence for
inspection.
The Subjects in Which Instruction Is Included in the Curriculum. The
Number of Students. Before, there were five levels in it, three lower and
two upper. Thus, the period of instruction was five years. But two more
levels have been added in order to establish a high standard, and the total
duration of education has been set at seven years. Along with French,
education in the Greek and Armenian languages is also compulsory in
this college. Arabic and Persian, too, are included in the curriculum of
education, but are not compulsory. [68] The subjects that are taught are
as follows: history and geography; electricity, and so on; physics; political
economy; the principles of law; the laws of Europe. Education in all these
subjects is at an extremely high level. I saw the history course myself. It was
in six thick volumes. Those educated at this college are appointed to very
high offices. Accordingly, so far more than two hundred have already been
appointed to regional offices, some of whom hold offices of an extremely
high rank. The number of students who are receiving education in the col-
lege at this time is more than six hundred.
The Cleanliness and Furnishings of the Dining Room. I toured the col-
lege thoroughly. Although the manager of the college, who is an esteemed
Turk, does not understand Arabic, because there was an interpreter with
me, we were able to communicate without difficulty. In the colleges here,
I generally noticed and liked very much that the manager was a man of
esteemed rank, and respect and dignity were expressed by his social com-
portment. The manager’s room, too, was organized and well-arranged,
as usual. When I arrived at the college, it was break hour, and the boys

Constantinople 69
were busy playing cricket. After a little while, when the boys came back
to class, the manager ṣāḥib took me on a tour of all the rooms of the col-
lege. The dining room was arranged with extreme propriety. There was an
extremely clean cloth spread on the table, and elaborate dishes had been
beautifully set out. The carafes, which were in accordance with the num-
ber of students, were generally made of glass and, one might say, served to
decorate the table. In the room for education in chemistry, and so on, there
were instruments of the highest degree, [69] and they were in abundance.
In the same series of buildings there is a very small masjid. Its building is
not very remarkable, but because a Turkish carpet of extremely superior
grade was spread inside and out, it seemed beautiful and adorned. On one
side, an excellent fragment of writing in Naskh script was hanging on the
wall. By inquiry, I learned that it was written by the hand of the deceased
Sulṭān ‘Abd al-‘Azīz.45 It is extremely excellent script.
Preparation for Namāz. Meanwhile, it came time for midday prayers. The
Muslim boys (there is no shortage of Christian boys, too, here) prepared
for namāz. They were generally wearing coat and pants, and their per-
forming ablutions with respect and resolution in that dress, and going into
the masjid line by line with dignity and reverence left a wondrous impres-
sion on my heart. The truth is that if Muslims make progress having been
freed from religious influence, then decline is a thousand degrees better
than such progress. After namāz, a sermon took place for a little while, but
very few boys participated in it.
Classical Education and Classical Madrasas
As we have already written above, education among the Turks began along
with the start of the sultanate. This was the very education that today is
remembered by the name “classical education.” No doubt, in some era
it was at the highest level. Thus, the original writings of Afz¨al al-Dīn
Khūnajī, ‘Allāmah Qūshjī, Chalabī, Khwājah-zādah, Ḥājjī Khalīfah, and
so on, exist even today as monuments to it.46 But the present education has
reached such an extreme of baseness that the education in our Hindustan
is a blessing in comparison with it. The thought that laid waste to all my

70 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
joys and happinesses [70] on this journey was the miserable state of clas-
sical education. This issue is touched upon in Hindustan, too, these days,
and anguish and regret are felt generally at the miserable state of classi-
cal education, but my regret was a regret of a different kind. The anguish
and regret that the new-educated of our country express at the old educa-
tion is in reality not anguish at all, but rather derision and delight in the
suffering of others. Although I like new education, and I like it from my
heart, I am still a staunch supporter of old education, and my thought is
that old education is necessary, and seriously necessary, for maintaining
the nationhood of Muslims. Along with that, when I see that the way this
education is put into practice is completely profitless and meaningless, I
cannot help but feel extreme anguish. In Hindustan, I managed to endure
by the thought that a lack of patronage and resources for something that
is not under the government’s shadow of benevolence is a natural matter.
However, seeing this situation in Constantinople, Syria, and Egypt, I often
felt severe anguish.
The Number of Students. The Livelihood of the Students. Boarding.
To make a long story short, classical education is abundantly prevalent
here, and because students of this kind are clearly recognized by their
fashion and dress, one can easily gain an estimate of their abundance in
masjids and common thoroughfares. Some people told me that in Con-
stantinople itself their number is no less than twenty thousand. Their
means of living is not only regrettable, but shocking. In all the (classi-
cal) madrasas of this place, there is a continuous holiday of three months
which begins with auspicious Ramz¨ān. In these months, the students
leave Constantinople and acquire zakāt in the villages and rural towns.
This zakāt is their income for the entire year. [71] In some madrasas—and
they are few and far between—they receive some bread, too, but there is
absolutely no arrangement for clothes, and so on. For living, there are the
madrasas’ rooms, which are extremely small, cramped, and dark.
The layout of the madrasas is as follows. There is a very small court-
yard, and on three sides of it there are small rooms. In the courtyard, there
is a cistern where they sit and perform ablutions. The rooms in the large
madrasas that the sulṭāns (Muḥammad Fātiḥ and Sulaimān, and so on)

Constantinople 71
built and are still standing today are extensive and spacious, but the rooms
of all other madrasas are so small and confined that one suffocates as one
goes inside. Despite all these things, I should acknowledge the generosity
of the Turks in promoting knowledge because, even if of a low degree, at
least hundreds of intellectual-scientific monuments exist today, and the
fair truth is that with respect to the period which these madrasas memo-
rialize, they are not unsuited to the culture and civilization of the time.
In our Hindustan, which, with its vastness and breadth, is itself a clime
in its own right, not a single intellectual-scientific monument of the six-
hundred-year period of the rule of Islam is found.
Curriculum of Instruction. The biggest complaint about classical educa-
tion is that the standard of education has been set extremely low. There is
no trace of the science of literature. Īsāghūjī and Shamsiyah are the con-
cluding books in logic and philosophy.47 It is difficult to find a madrasa in
which the ṣiḥāḥ sittah are taught.48 The science of meaning and rhetoric,
and the principles of jurisprudence, too, are in the same state. Of course,
there is a great deal of attention paid to fiqh, but education in it, too, is not
innovative.49 Rather, it is extremely common and imitative. [72] I came to
know several maulawīs. They always talked about such trivial and general
issues that I felt both surprise and disappointment.
The Scientific State of the Turks
The Scientific State of the Turks. The Translation of Books into the
Turkish Language. If the regional languages in the parts of the world
where Islam ruled did not completely disappear, then it certainly hap-
pened that their scientific status was snatched from them and given to
Arabic. Although the regional languages of Hindustan, Persia, Spain, and
Afghanistan were completely different, Arabic alone remained the intel-
lectual-scientific language at each place, and is so even so now. The Turks,
too, are no exception to this general influence. But they are distinguished
among all Islamic nations by the particular characteristic that, along with
submission to Arabic, they also did not allow their own language to be
deprived of intellectual-scientific treasure. In the age in which the classical

72 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
sciences ruled, an entire series of those sciences existed in the Turkish lan-
guage, and still does. I saw with eyes of wonder that the histories of Ibn-i
Khaldūn, Ṭabarī, Ibn-i Khallikān, Maqrīzī, and so on, which are extremely
thick books, and among which some are in seven volumes each—transla-
tions of all of them exist in Turkish.50 By contrast, one cannot find even a
single example of this in Fāris or Afghanistan. If mention were made of
translated books apart from original compositions in Turkish, one would
have to prepare a large catalogue.
A Turkish friend of mine, who is an expert in numerous languages,
recounted to me as a factual account [73] (not a boastful one) that histo-
ries, dramas, novels, travelogues, and books on stylistics and rhetoric in
the French language have been translated in such abundance into Turkish
that it is no exaggeration to say that France’s entire field of literary studies
and has entered the Turkish language. Hundreds of books of modern arts
and sciences, too, have already been translated, and it is for this reason
that in all the colleges of Turkey, except for the Imperial College, educa-
tion in these arts and sciences takes place in the Turkish language, and
takes place at the highest level.
Historical Writings in Turkish. The practice of original, independent
writing, too, is not lacking. Books on all the branches of the arts and sci-
ences are being written in abundance, and the books that are taught in
colleges and schools are generally original writings, not translations. How
could I have found the time and opportunity to acquire acquaintance with
all modern original writings? Of course, in accordance with my taste, I
did look at books on history and rijāl, on the basis of which I can say that,
besides Arabic, such historical material does not exist in any language of
Asia.51 Rather, in one respect, it is superior to Arabic. All the histories in
the Arabic language are a collection of simple facts and events, and what-
ever effort and care there is, it is only related to the principles of narra-
tive transmission. By contrast, Turkish histories are written in accordance
with the principles and rules that are the principles of historical philoso-
phy, and on the basis of which Europe has taken this subject to the peak of
perfection. I took a cursory look at the history book that is included in the
course of studies at the Civil College. In all points of fact, it has carefully

Constantinople 73
considered the chain of causation, made judgments by weighing evidence,
and employed discernment and criticism throughout. Along with that, at
the end of each period of rule, the civilizational, moral, and intellectual-
scientific state of the period has been shown in detail. [74]
Biography, Meaning Rijāl and Tarājim.
52 Qāmūs al-a‘lām. There is an
extremely useful series of biographies the name of which is Mashāhīr-i
Rijāl [The Famous among Men]. They have written information about the
lives of famous people of achievement extremely finely and in a pleasing
style. Unfortunately, this series was left incomplete. Otherwise, it would
have been an extremely useful collection. A special kind of very large
encyclopedia, the name of which is Qāmūs al-a‘lām [Dictionary of the Sci-
ences], is in preparation these days.53 In addition to biographical studies
of men, it also includes entries on famous cities, buildings, and historical
places. A list of the writings in Arabic and French, and so on, on which the
author has relied is included with it. I read the names of the Arabic books.
They are extremely rare and reliable books and are not available anywhere
except Constantinople. This book is arranged in alphabetical order and, at
this time, has come to the letter ze.
The Progress of Geography. Along with history, geography, too, has
enjoyed extreme progress. A great many useful books have been written.
So many large maps and charts of the entire world and different populated
areas have been prepared that it is unlikely that so many exist in any part
of the world other than Europe. The maps are extremely standardized,
beautiful, and elegant, and are not inferior to the maps prepared in Europe
in any regard. Turks have a special interest in this field.
The Abundance of Turkish Writings. I cannot tell you the sufficient stan-
dard of the majority of Turkish writings, but one time in the office of the
Department of Education, I took a cursory look at the catalogue of books
that were published in Constantinople alone in just the period of a single
month. Their number was nearly two thousand. Although among them
were also books in Armenian, Greek, French, and other languages, [75]
the Turkish writings had the largest share. Still, it is regrettable that among

74 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
them novels and dramas were more numerous, and this is the same afflic-
tion that is spread throughout our unfortunate region.
Turkish Literature. Turkish literature, too, has made extreme progress,
and it is a strange thing that, in many characteristics, it resembles our
Urdu. Turkey’s classical literature, in the manner of classical Urdu, was
colorful, elaborate, filled with metaphors, and restricted to rhyme. But
now, like new Urdu, there is regard for simplicity, clarity, and an apropos
quality, and new original compositions are written in exactly this style.
The inventors or masters of this new style are Kamāl Bey, Ḥāmid Bey,
Professor Nājī, and so on.54 When I began studying Turkish, I intended to
read classical compositions. But my friends, who were also my teachers,
said that the difference between classical and modern Turkish is that of
the earth and the sky, and learning the classical language would not be
sufficient for the new language. Professor Vámbéry,55 in the lecture that
he has given on the present civilization of the Turks, having compared
classical and modern Turkish, has acknowledged with astonishment the
attractiveness, clarity, and simplicity of the present language.
Turkish Writers. Among Turkish writers, these are the names of the most
renowned and distinguished figures of the day: Aḥmad Midḥat, Jaudat
Pāshā, Professor Nājī, ‘Abū al-Z ¨iyā, Sāmī, ‘Alī Nuṣrat. Professor Nājī is a
poet, and you might say he is the poet of the capital. There is no office of
malik al-shu‘arā here.56 Otherwise, he would have received this title. Still,
he is considered the poet of the capital. Aḥmad Midḥat is a major author.57
[76] He has written an extremely detailed history of the Turkish govern-
ment, which is in twelve volumes. In response to the objections that are
made against Islam, he has written a detailed book, which is in three vol-
umes and is named Mudāfa‘ah-i Islāmiyah.
58 In addition to Turkish, Farsi,
and Arabic, he has mastery in the French language. He was appointed as
a representative on behalf of Turkey in numerous sessions of the Oriental
Conference that has been established in Europe, and in the Stockholm
Conference it was he to whom official authority over the departments of
Arabic, Farsi, and so on, was given. Aḥmad Jaudat Pāshā is an extremely

Constantinople 75
esteemed person, and is a member, meaning he is a wazīr and yāwar, of
the assembly of wazīrs.59 His age is close to sixty or seventy, and because,
along with being aged, he is weak in body and frail, he participates less
in the assembly of wazīrs.60 Among his writings, Qawā‘id-i ‘Us˙māniyah,
which is on Turkish morphology and syntax, is included in the course. I
met him. We kept company for a while. He can speak in Arabic and Per-
sian without difficulty. He spoke to me in Arabic.61 The great praiseworthy
thing about him is that despite his wealth, power, and office of wazīrate,
he lives an extremely simple life and mostly keeps busy with intellectual-
scientific activities.
Newspapers and Journals. In mentioning Turkish literature, it is also nec-
essary to discuss newspapers and monthly journals, because these things
are considered a major part of literature these days. I say with regret that,
in this respect, Turkish literature is in a state of baseness. Turkish-lan-
guage newspapers are not few in number. There are a great many daily
newspapers, and they come out with great luster and splendor. The dic-
tion, too, is very simple and polished. [77] A taste for newspapers has also
spread throughout the entire region. A great number of coffeehouses are
specifically for newspapers, where newspapers are always found in abun-
dance, and for this reason they are called a qir’at-khānah [reading room]
instead of qahwah-khānah [coffeehouse].
There is all this, but the thing that is the life of a newspaper, that is,
freedom, it does not exist here at all. There is nothing in all the newspapers
except for official ordinances and everyday news. The result of this is that
the Turkish language is completely deprived of a political style of writing
and the power of reasoned argument. And the reality is, how and by what
means can loftiness of thought, power of description, force of diction, pas-
sion, and efficacy come into a language in which the element of freedom
does not exist? Look at Arabic. As long as it was the period of the righteous
caliphate and natures were free and headstrong, Arabic was brimming
with passion and efficacy. From the time that the foundation of autocratic
government was laid and the family of the Banū Umayyah trampled and
crushed the freedom of Arabia with great power and force, neither that

76 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
efficacy nor that passion remained. No doubt, because of an abundance of
information, the literature of the subsequent period is extremely extensive
and rich. But sift through all the writings of that period. No trace of a free
style of writing, political passion, or efficacy is found.
The Reason for the Lack of Freedom in Newspapers. Along with all these
things, it is necessary for me to acknowledge that the newspapers’ lack of
freedom is necessitated by Turkey’s political circumstances. The difference
of religion among the citizens, the antagonism of foreign powers, interfer-
ences by adversaries, sensationalism in the newspapers, the proximity of
European governments—these are circumstances in which even the freest
of free governments would do the same as Turkey has done. [78] Hav-
ing seen the orders that the republican government of France just recently
implemented in Tunisia concerning the freedom of newspapers, who is
unjust enough to make accusations against Turkey?62
Obstruction in Printing Books.
63 Of course, the obstruction that exists
here concerning the printing of books is somewhat objectionable. The
general rule here is that when some person wants to publish a classical or
modern book, the book is first presented in the Department of Informa-
tion. There is a separate bureau of inspection and investigation there. The
officers of this bureau read the entire book from beginning to end, and,
in accordance with their report, sometimes the printing of the book is
stopped, or erasure and emendation is made. The need for this rule arose
because some people act in extremely bad faith in printing books. For
example, when the Christians in Beirut printed Alfāẓ al-kitābiyah,
64 wher-
ever there were āyats of the Pure Quran and, in accordance with Islamic
practice, the headings were qāl Allāh65 or kamā fī al-Qur’ān al-majīd,
66
they changed them everywhere and made them kamā qīl67 or kamā qāl
al-Qur’ān,
68 whereas such words about the Glorious Quran could not have
issued from the pen of a Muslim. More than that, these same Christians
have printed a selection of the Quran, and wherever in some āyat there is
mention of an event that opposes Christian narratives, they have written
in parentheses that “it is wrong and this way is correct.” No doubt, an
Islamic sultanate cannot tolerate interpolations of this kind, and this is the

Constantinople 77
reason that extreme caution and investigation is employed by the sultanate
when publishing books. [79]
But it is regrettable that these days its method of application has trans-
gressed moderation. This department was established with the purpose of
stopping distortion and alteration, but sometimes it has acted on distortion
and alteration itself. Sharḥ-i ‘Aqā’id-i Nasafī was being printed in front of
me in a printing house.69 The Department of Information had censored all
the text in the book in which there was discussion of the caliphate and the
hadith al-aimma min Quraish is mentioned.70 The people at the printing
house were compelled to print this censored copy. I saw the original copy
on which the Department of Information made this manipulation, and I
recall that I lost control of myself because of frustration and anger at that
time. These people probably made this manipulation in the passion of, in
their own minds, well-wishing for the sulṭān, but if the acclaimed gentle-
man had been informed of it, he would never have approved of it.
As I have recounted above, the newspapers, at least, are not worthy
of attention, but the magazines and monthly journals that are issued
in the Turkish language are extremely valuable. The most famous and
renowned among them is Ma‘ārif, which is issued weekly.71 Articles of
the highest order are always written in this journal, and the people who
are masters of the modern sciences among the Turks nowadays mostly
demonstrate their achievement and perfection by means of this journal.
Articles are generally related to natural science and modern instruments,
and no issue is without illustration. The amount of distribution is not
small, either. When I inquired from the owner of the printing house, I
learned that five thousand copies are issued. Apart from Ma‘ārif, there are
other intellectual journals, and they are published extremely capably. [80]
˙
Among them, Rasamlī Ghazatah, Muṣawwar Jahān, and S
arwat-i Funūn
have passed before my eyes.72 In terms of paper, script, clarity, in short,
in external splendor, all of these journals compete with the renowned
journals of Europe.
There is no doubt that with respect to the daily progress that the arts
and sciences have made in Turkey, and the abundance with which new
writings continue to be published in each field, it has acquired the rank of
preeminence over the entire Asian world.

78 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Printing Houses
The printing houses are in extreme abundance here, and they are unex-
celled in fineness of script, clarity, and elegance. The Arabic script type
that exists, and which is the invention of the Turkish intellectual ‘Abū
al-Z ¨iyā, is considered incomparable throughout the world.73 Wherever
Arabic books are printed in the world today, the books printed in Beirut
are regarded as the most excellent. But the people in Beirut themselves
recounted to me that “in fact this type is the invention of the Turks, and
we are their imitators.” Because Turkish books are typically printed in
Constantinople, and they do not come into these regions, Beirut alone
has gained general renown. It is either the effect of affluence or general
appreciation that all the books printed in Constantinople are printed on
extremely excellent and expensive paper, as opposed to Egypt and Hindu-
stan, where paper for cleaning shoes is used for books. There is no other
reason for this except that in these regions, people still do not understand
the value and worth of knowledge. [81]
It is a matter of regret that there is no printing house here that is as
prominent and prosperous as is the Nawal Kishorī printing house in Hin-
dustan.74 Along with that, it is another matter of regret that most printing
houses belong to other nations. Even the owner of Ma‘ārif, which I have just
discussed, is a Christian. Among the printing houses that belong to Mus-
lims, Tarjumān-i Ḥaqīqat, Matba‘-i ‘Us˙māniyah, and Shirkat-i Ṣaḥāfiyah
are the most distinguished. I toured all of them. Shirkat-i Ṣahāfiyah is
remarkable with respect to the fact that it has been founded on shared cap-
ital, and all its shareholders are Muslims. The sum of its capital is eighteen
thousand pounds, meaning nearly two lakh rupees. All the work is done
by an engine. The engine is very large and runs ten or twelve machines.
Just as I arrived, Sharḥ-i Bukhārī by ‘Ainī was being printed.75 Two thick
volumes had already been prepared by that time. The people at the print-
ing house said that there were eight more just like it. In all of Constanti-
nople, this is the Muslims’ only shared workhouse. Otherwise, first, why
would Muslims touch commerce at all, and even if by some chance they
had, why would a few people have come together to do it? In this respect,
this printing house, in a way, is an extraordinary occurrence.76

Constantinople 79
Libraries
Because of thematic arrangement and discursive order, I have reached this
heading late; otherwise, with respect to personal interest and the purpose of
the journey, this was the topic that I would have written first and in the most
detail. The truth is that among the intellectual achievements of the Turks,
the most worthy of pride are these libraries. The parts of the Islamic world in
which there is talk of education and learning today are [82] Hindustan, Ara-
bia, Egypt, Syria, the countries of the Maghrib, Persia, and Iran. I have seen
the intellectual-scientific resource of most of them with my own eyes, and
those that I have not seen I know by such strong means that it is as good as
seeing them. On this basis, I can say with sufficient certainty that Constan-
tinople is the largest center of Arabic writings in the entire Islamic world.
The Number of Libraries and Books. The number of all the libraries
that are in this city is forty-five. The royal library, which is in the Qaṣr-i
Humāyūn [Royal Palace] and is extremely old, is in addition to them.77
These libraries house a total of eighty-five thousand books. Although this
number is not such a large number—there are probably more books than
that in our Hindustan—Constantinople is superior in terms of the excel-
lence and rarity of the books. Among these libraries, the names of a few
are recorded as follows: Jāmi‘ Āyā Sofiyah Library; Jāmi‘ Bāyazīd Library;
Yol Jāmi‘ Library; Old Ḥamīdiyah Library; ‘Āshir Āfandī, Shaikh al-Islām,
Library; As‘ad Āfandī, Naqīb al-ashrāf, Library; Jāmi‘ Muḥammad
Fātiḥ Library; New Ḥamīdiyah Library; ‘Alī Pāshā Shahīd Library; Nūr
‘Us˙māniyah Library; Lālah Bī Library; Ḥakīm Ughlī ‘Alī Pāshā Library;
Muḥammad Pāshā Kūprulī Library; Qalīch ‘Alī Pāshā Library; Walī
al-Dīn Āfandī Library; Salīmiyah Library; Faiz¨ullāh Āfandī Library;
Sulṭān Muḥammad Qaz¨ī-zādah Library; Wālidah Sulṭān Mosque Library;
‘Āṭif Āfandī Library; Shāh-zādah Dāmād Ibrāhīm Pāshā Library; Khus-
rau Pāshā Library; Mihrshān Library; [83] Muḥammad Āfandī Library;
Muṣṭafā Āfandī Library; Taufīq Āfandī Library; Sulaimāniyah Library;
Muḥammad Āfandī Murād Library; Rāghib Pāshā Library.78 Detailed cat-
alogues of fourteen of these libraries have been printed and published, and
the remaining catalogues, too, will probably be published in time.

80 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Endowments for Libraries. As their names themselves express, these
libraries were founded by former pāshās and amīrs, and all of them are
public endowments. Along with each library, property, too, is endowed,
from which its ordinary expenses—meaning renovations and repair of the
building, carpet and ordinary furniture, and the salary of employees—are
paid. With regard to these matters, one must acknowledge that the rank of
the Turks in the generous support of knowledge is superior to all Islamic
nations. In India, an Islamic government lasted for ages and was prosper-
ous and glorious. Great renowned wazīrs and amīrs came and went, but
today not even one intellectual-scientific monument of theirs exists.
In these libraries one also finds proof of the fact that among the Turks,
the group of amīrs (which in other nations is in generally a relatively illit-
erate group) is educated, and educated at the highest level. In most librar-
ies, there exist the personal writings of the endowers, or books written
in their hands, which bear witness to their taste and breadth of vision.
Additionally, from the kind of excellent and rare books that have been
sought out and collected, one gains an estimate of the fact [84] that the
intellectual-scientific taste of the collectors was no ordinary taste.
The External State of the Libraries. These libraries are of an ordinary
grade with respect to the fineness of the building and other resources and
provisions. So much so that in some libraries, there are not even cabi-
nets. They have piled books on a platform around which there is an iron
enclosure. In all the libraries, seating is on the floor. Of course, there is
just this much formality: benches are arranged in front, on which they
set books and read. Although the Ḥamīdiyah Library, which has recently
been established and is a monument to the auspicious age of the Great
Sulṭān, is of greater magnificence and glory—the building is beautiful and
large; there are silken pillows on all the desks, chairs, and couches; in sum,
it is an exception to other libraries in all matters—still, it cannot compete
with the Allahabad Public Library.79
The Administration of Endowments. Because the administration of all
endowments is connected with the state, the libraries, too, are under the

Constantinople 81
care of the government, and this is the reason that, despite the length of
time, the books are so carefully protected that not even a single page has
been lost. The employees, despite their meager salaries, are extremely hon-
est and of upright character. The endowment of the ‘Āshir Āfandī Library
is so small that the librarian cannot receive more than ordinary food and
two rupees per month. But the person who has been appointed librarian
is so honest and so observant of his duties that it is not possible to be more
so. Grapevines have grown on the walls of the library. One day I said to
him, “If you just sold all the grapes, you could have a reasonable income.”
He said, “According to the condition of the endower, [85] these grapes are
only for the people who came to the library for the purpose of reading
books, so I cannot gain any kind of benefit from them.” Because of his
meager salary, the poor fellow has not even married, nor does he have a
place to live. He sleeps right there in the library at night.
Several Characteristics of the Libraries. The characteristics and sum-
mary details of the libraries will be known by the following facts:
(1) The Soundness and Excellence of Manuscript Copies. The greatest
distinction is that the books that are found here are generally in old script,
authentic, and corrected by past masters. The authenticity of classical and
rare books of which there are only a few copies in the world takes pre-
cedence over all else. Otherwise, one cannot rely on them. There is no
lack of old books in the libraries of Egypt, too, but most have been writ-
ten in the present period, and for this reason they are not very authentic
or reliable. Having seen the books at Constantinople, one wonders from
where have such wondrous copies of these books been gathered? I had
been searching for ‘Abd al-Qāhir al-Jurjānī’s Asrār al-balāghah for some
time.80 I found only one copy in Hindustan, but it was extremely errone-
ous and unreliable. I saw numerous copies of it in Constantinople, and
all of them were extremely sound and in old script. Similarly, copies of
al-Bayān wal-tabyīn by al-Jāḥiẓ, Tażkirah by Ibn-i Ḥamadūn, Mu‘ jim
al-Udabā’ by Ya‘qūt Ḥamawī, Kitāb al-ashrāf by al-Balāżurī, and Tārīkh-i
kabīr by Imām Bukhārī all exist and are extremely authentic and reliable.

82 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
(2) The Excellence of the Script and the Paper’s Being Zar-afshān. In
some libraries, for example in the Old Ḥamidiyah, there is the distinction
that the paper of most books is zarīn or zar-afshān,81 and there are golden
flower and vine designs in the margins. Along with these formalities, the
script is of an extremely high order. Because books of the classical age
could rarely be found with such formalities, the founder of the library has
had most of them prepared with care. I had numerous books, which even
included a complete copy of Shifā by Bū ‘Alī Sīnā, taken out, and I looked at
them and spontaneously praised the refinement of the owner of the library.
(3) The Translation of Greek Books. I thought that the translations that
were made of Greek and Egyptian books in the period of Abbasid rule had
disappeared from the world. But when I came here, the falsehood of this
idea was proven. Although relative to the large amount of translations that
were made, the existing material may as well be nonexistent, still, what
little does exist is a blessing.82
It seems that the Turks paid special attention to classical writings.
Thus, in this matter, they took advantage of European efforts, too. Ibn-i
Rushd had written an extremely beneficial and comprehensive summary
of Aristotle’s writings. This original summary has been lost. But a transla-
tion of it was made in Latin, which is still found in the libraries of Europe.
As‘ad Āfandī, a Turkish intellectual, translated the Latin summary into
Arabic and made some additions throughout. I saw this translation in the
library of Rāghib Pāshā. It is a very large collection and is an excellent
specimen of the intellectual-scientific endeavors of the Turks.
(4) Rare Works of History and Literature. In the fields of history and
literature, I saw several writings in which the innovation that I had been
seeking for some time was found and, apart from the present writings
of Europe, no trace of this kind of writing style had been found any-
where. For example, many books have been written on the circumstances
of qāz¨īs, [87] but no one thought to copy their rulings and decrees along
with their life circumstances so that one could compare this with today’s
method of deciding cases. A book of this kind exists in the Library of
the Yanī Congregational Mosque. The author of the book is Abū Bakr

Constantinople 83
Muḥammad bin Khalaf Wakī‘,83 an author from an extremely ancient
period, who recounts all events with an unbroken chain of authority. In
the book, he has observed the rule to copy, along with information about
each person, a great many rulings and judgments, and has recounted the
specifics of the cases.
I had never seen a book of this kind in the field of literature; rather,
I did not even think that a Muslim would ever have written a book in
which there was a history of poetic themes; that is, such-and-such a poet
first wrote such and such a theme, then, gradually, such and such a poet
made this and that addition, or changed its forms thus. In the Library of
‘Āshir Āfandī, I saw a very thick book specifically on this topic. The author
has claimed that the pre-Islamic Arabs invented themes of every kind,
then later poets developed them and came up with various new embel-
lishments. The entire book is in proof of this claim. The author copies one
poem by a pre-Islamic Arab for each theme and tells us that among the
Islamic poets, such and such a poet changed this same theme a bit and
wrote it thus. Then the poets of the Umayyad and Abbasid governments
produced even more forms from it. Having read this book, one is aston-
ished by the author’s breadth of vision and discernment of subtle detail,
and, along with that, one regrets that later authors could not follow in the
footsteps of [88] rare compositions of this kind so that numerous books on
this subject might exist today.84
(5) The Writings of Philosophers and the Leaders of Their Fields. The
abundance in which the books of renowned philosophers and leaders of
their fields are found here cannot be found anywhere else. The rare writ-
ings of Imām Ghazālī, Bū ‘Alī Sīnā, Fakhr-i Rāzī, and Fārābī, whose names
are known only by means of Ibn-i Khallikān, and so on, are found here
in abundance. The correspondence and letters related to gnosis and truth
that occurred between Abū ‘Alī Sīnā and Ḥaz¨rat Sulṭān Abū Sa‘īd Abū al-
Khair from time to time are available in the form of short treatises.85
Regarding Ibn-i Sīnā, it has long been a matter of debate whether
or not he added anything to Greek philosophy. He has written in Kitāb
al-shifā, “Whatever I write is the philosophy of Aristotle. I have written
my own philosophy in Ḥikmat-i mashriqiyah.” Europeans are desperately

84 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
seeking this book, meaning Ḥikmat-i mashriqiyah. And because they can-
not find this book, Professor Munk has written in his book, Rabṭ falsafat
al-Yahūd wal-Islam, that we cannot find Ḥikmat-i mashriqiyah, and from
the books we can find, it is proven that Ibn-i Sina did not add anything.86
An extremely excellent copy of this rare book is found in the Library of the
Āyā Ṣofīyah [Hagia Sophia] Congregational Mosque. Would Muslims ever
have taken the trouble to read it and to compare it with Greek philosophy?
But if Europeans had found this book, there is no doubt that a conclu-
sive decision in the debate as to whether or not Muslims added anything
to Greek philosophy would have been made. Because time was short, I
looked only superficially at this book. It did not appear that there was any
innovation in it. [89] If there had been an opportunity to look at it with
eyes of minute examination, then some opinion could have been formed.
The Names of Some Books of History and Literature. Among the rare
books of history and literature that I saw here, the names of some of them
are as follows: Tārīkh by Khaṭīb Baghdādī, whole and complete; Tārīkh-i
Islām by ‘Allāmah Żahabī, eight volumes; Tārīkh al-ḥukamā by Jamāl
al-Dīn Qifṭī;87 Tārīkh-i kabīr by Imām Bukhārī, three volumes; Tajārib al-
umam by Ibn-i Miskawaih;88 Muntaẓam by Ibn al-Jauzī; Mira’t al-zamān
by Sibṭ ibn al-Jauzī; Masālik al-abṣār by Ibn-i Faz¨lullāh, twenty volumes;
‘Iqd al-jumān by Badr al-Dīn al-‘Ainī, eighteen volumes; Mukhtaṣar-i
Tārīkh-i Dimashq-i Ibn-i ‘Asākir by Jamāl al-Dīn bin Mukarrim al-Anṣārī,
four volumes; Riḥlah by Ibn-i Khaldūn; Nihāyat al-arab by al-Nuwairī;
Tabaqāt al-udabā by Yāqūt al-Ḥamawī;89 Tabaqāt al-kubrā by Ibn-i
Sa‘d;90 Tabaqāt al-umam by Ibn-i Ṣā‘id al-Andalūsī; Kitāb al-ashrāf by
al-Balāżurī, whole and complete; Sīrat al-‘Umarain by Ibn-i Jauzī;91 Kitāb
al-bayān wal-tab’īn by Jāḥiẓ;92 Ṣinā‘atain by al-‘Askarī; Dalā’il al-i‘ jāz by
‘Abd al-Qāhir al-Jurjānī;93 the Tażkirah by Ibn-i Ḥamdūn; Sharḥ-i Tabrīzī
bar Dīwān-i Abū Tammām;94 the Dīwān of Abū Nuwās, complete; Sirqāt
al-Mutanabbī by Ibn al-‘Umaid;95 Majmū‘ah-i risā’il by Abū Isḥāq Ṣābī.96
The People97 of This Place Do Not Take Advantage of the Libraries. In
mentioning libraries, I am forced say with extreme regret that these rare
books are entirely useless here. First, these libraries open for only a few

Constantinople 85
hours in the day. Along with that, there is a continuous holiday for a few
months in the year. Along with these things, there is such a lack of superior
taste that rare and classical books just lie there, unused. No one even picks
them up to look at them. In the libraries, whenever I saw people engaged
in studying books, I always sought to discover what kind of books they
were reading. But I never saw any books other than Mukhtaṣar-i ma‘ānī,
Īsāghūjī, Sharḥ-i waqāyah, Jalālain, and so on.98 [90] Of course, renowned
scholars from foreign countries appear from time to time, and they are
always in search of rare and excellent books.
The reality is that in the entire Islamic world, the method of education
has become so debased that, apart from a few textbooks, no one has any
inclination toward modern knowledge of any kind, the result of which is
that the material of novelty and innovation is being stripped away from
the nation, and there is no hope in the future for whatever little remains.
Note: The detailed account that I gave in description of the libraries, I
made for a specific purpose, and I want to call the nation’s attention to it.
In Europe, numerous societies have been established whose aim is to col-
lect classical, excellent books and print and publish them. It is by virtue of
these societies that classical and rare Arabic books have become available
to us which we had never thought obtainable. These are the societies that
compiled a complete copy of Tārīkh-i kabīr by Abū Ja‘far Jarīr Ṭabarī and
have printed and published a great number of volumes of it,99 whereas the
scholars of Egypt and Turkey had lost all hope of finding this rare histori-
cal treasure, and Shāh ‘Abd al-‘Azīz sāḥib had assured us that it had been
lost from the world.100 Without a doubt, Europe has done us a great favor,
and we should acknowledge it openly. I beseech the elders of the nation
to form a grand society of this kind. Sufficient capital should be collected
by means of public donations. Capable and qualified authors should be
appointed as members for the selection of books. Books should be copied
and ordered from Constantinople and Egypt, and they should be printed
and published. [91] Such an undertaking may appear overwhelming and,
with regard to the present state of the nation, impossible. But in reality
it is not. If among four crore Muslims, even one hundred Muslims are
prepared to give a small amount in subscription, then it is no difficulty for
this task to be accomplished.

86 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
We hope that the society that has been established in Hyderabad by
the name of Dā’irat al-Ma‘ārif al-Dakaniyah, of which one esteemed mem-
ber is Nawāb Iqbāl Yār Jang Bahādur, will attend to our request.101 We
recognize with gratitude its generous support of science and knowledge,
but we require more generosity than this, and our hope is that the Dā’irat
al-Ma‘ārif will attend to this purpose with even more attention and care.
Zawāyā or Hostels
Hostels, which they call takyah or takāyā here, are in abundance.102 The
names of 305 hostels, along with details of their locations and other infor-
mation, are recorded in the latest report that has been compiled. But the
word khānqāh [retreat for dervishes] does not carry the same meaning
that is used in our region. In these regions, this is a wondrously beneficent
practice that is, in truth, amazing. In all major cities, there are separate
hostels for every region and every group. When a traveler from that region
and group turns up there, he can enter the hostel without hindrance of
any kind and can stay there as long as he desires. Food and one serving
of tea each day are free. This generosity is so widespread that despite the
remoteness of the distance and the lack of connection, in Constantinople,
Damascus, Jerusalem, Aleppo, Mosul, Diyar Bakır, all these places, there
are separate hostels for Hindustanis, [92] and an appropriate quantity of
meat and grain is designated for them.
Amīrs and elites have established these hostels and have endowed
enough property that regular expenses are always paid. There is a shaikh
in every hostel who receives a reasonable salary and board, and the entire
administration of the hostel depends on him. I visited numerous hostels.
The buildings of some of them were of pleasant ambiance and elegant.
The type and quantity of food is also sufficient. The yearly expenses of the
hostels in Constantinople alone cannot be estimated at less than four or
five lakhs. In truth, this is very great proof of the generosity of the Turks
and there is no doubt that, with regard to the time when this practice was
established, it was neither unsuitable nor inelegant.
You have probably read in Arabic histories that there always remained
a steady stream of travelers and students throughout the Islamic regions.

Constantinople 87
This was on account of these hostels and zawāyā. Ibn-i Baṭūṭah was aided
by this practice on his worldwide journey. Thus, he wrote the names of
these hostels in his travelogue. But it is a fact of nature that when bad
days befall a nation, beneficial practices become harmful. Muslims lost
the taste for travel, geographical research, and the acquisition of knowl-
edge. For this reason, this custom has become nothing more than a means
of laziness, freeloading, and pauperism, and it is doing extreme harm to
national life. I went into and saw many hostels myself. Some travelers have
been there for several years. They have neither any occupation nor any
work. Here, one can see with one’s own eyes the condition of the officers of
Lucknow that we always used to hear about.103 [93] The shaikhs to whom
the administration of the hostels is entrusted, and the cash and commodi-
ties in their care, are generally double-dealing and dishonest. They live
in extreme ease and luxury themselves and do not give the travelers half,
a third, or even a quarter of the amount that is designated for them. The
shaikh of the Indian hostel is a Kashmiri gentleman. He has taken several
wives. He has built a house separate from the hostel for himself. He often
stays there. The two and a half seers of meat that are allotted for the hostel
each day come into the possession of the gentleman, and even ordinary
food does not fall to the lot of the travelers. The building of the hostel is
crumbling. There is always a pile of trash and filth sitting in the courtyard.
In brief, it is a complete picture of savagery and desolation. Although the
other hostels that I saw were better than the Hindi hostel in every respect,
no trace of honesty and integrity is found. In this way, an amount of sev-
eral lakhs annually is squandered in an extremely bad way.
Congregational Masjids and Famous Places
With respect to the abundance of congregational masjids and their fine-
ness of construction, magnificence, and glory, Constantinople has no
equal in the world. From the time of Muḥammad Fātiḥ, who was the first
to sit on the throne in this capital city, up to today, a congregational mas-
jid of all the rulers who have passed (with a few exceptions) is found, and
each is of great grandeur and glory. Among them the most distinguished
are the Jāmi‘ Fātiḥ, the Jāmi‘ Sulaimān, the Jāmi‘ Bāyazid, the Jāmi‘

88 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Wālidah-i Sulṭān, the Jāmi‘ Sulṭān Aḥmad, and the Jāmi‘ Āyā Sofiyah,
and among these the Jāmi‘ Āyā Sofiyah is the most glorious and magnifi-
cent. [94] The construction of these masjids is completely different from
the masjids in our place. There is neither a hall nor arches nor a courtyard.
There is only a single dome, but so large that several thousand people can
fit under it. Although with respect to Hindustani taste, one cannot call
these masjids beautiful and elegant, the boundless largeness of the dome
and the loftiness of the building immediately fill a person with wonder,
rather, render him awed and wonderstruck. There are metal chandeliers
of several hundred candles in each masjid. It seems as if the tradition of
the chandelier exists from a very ancient time. In the Arabic histories of
Spain, this kind of chandelier is probably meant by the word s˙urayyā.
104
Of course, the difference is that they were made of glass and crystal there,
and they are made of metal here. Generally, in all masjids there is a special
compulsory element from which it seems that the sulṭāns were extremely
excessive in Sunnism and made a display of it at every turn. Generally, in
every masjid there are four large shields in all four corners, and, on them,
written in gold in extremely fine calligraphy and large, bold letters, are
Abū Bakr, ‘Umar, ‘Us˙mān, and ‘Alī,
105 in entirely the same way that they
hang calligraphed fragments written by masters on walls for decoration
and adornment.
The Decoration of the Masjids. All masjids are elaborate and decorated.
Ordinarily, reed mats, and on Friday and both Eids, excellent and highly
valuable carpets are laid out on the floor. On one side of the masjid, some
land is reserved on which there is a place for ablutions with flowing water. I
was extremely pleased by the fact that pools are absolutely not in use here.
The Āyā Ṣofiyah [Hagia Sofia] Mosque. The Āyā Ṣofiyah Mosque is the
most glorious, and all masjids are built on its example. Originally, it was a
very large church, which Constantine constructed in 325. Its construction
took seven years, and one hundred architects and ten thousand laborers
worked on it. [95] Muḥammad Fātiḥ, having altered it somewhat, turned
it into a masjid. Ibn-i Baṭūṭah had seen it as a church. He writes, “This is
the largest church of the Romans, and because no outsider can go inside it,

Constantinople 89
I cannot describe the quality of its interior. From the outside, its features
are that there is a compound of one mile, and the entire ground is covered
in marble flooring. In the middle is a canal on both shores of which there
is a wall of marble one arm’s length high. On the wall is excellent mosaic
work, and extremely excellent flowers and vine patterns have been made.
The gate of the church is covered in gold leaf and silver leaf. It became clear
from peoples’ accounts that several thousand priests and monks live in the
church, day and night.”
The features that Ibn-i Baṭūṭah described, alas, no longer exist. The
enclosure, in which there was a canal, is completely outside the masjid,
and has been turned into a coffeehouse.
Truly, this building is wondrous and astonishing. The diameter of the
middle dome is 115 feet, and the elevation of the ceiling is 180 feet. There
are 170 columns, and all the stones are marble and porphyry stone. The
diameter of these columns is no less than three or four arm’s lengths each.
On the gate, which is from the time of Constantine and is made of copper,
some images from the classical age are made, and they are still standing.
Even remnants of the images of Jesus, peace be upon him, and Mary that
were on the ceiling still exist.
Places Worth Seeing. Places worth seeing are many. For example, ancient
temples of the Greeks; the armory; the treasury, meaning where there are
full-sized images of all the Ottoman sulṭāns along with original dress,
weapons, and jewelry; the factory for casting canons; [96] mūzah khānah,
106
meaning the ancient museum where there are rocks and inscriptions of an
extremely ancient period. In it, there is even the coffin of Alexander the
Greek, and so on, and so on. But I could not visit most places. Thus, I shall
content myself with those places that I toured myself.
Shipyard [Tars-khānah]. That is, the factory for building ships. It is a very
large, magnificent factory, and because it is connected with the Military
Department, no one can go there without the written permission of the
Naval Office. Fortunately, one esteemed officer in the Naval Office was
an acquaintance of our friend Shaikh ‘Alī Ẓabyān. He kindly sent an offi-
cer along with us, who took us on a thorough tour of the entire factory.

90 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
This ṣāḥib understood and spoke Arabic well, and for this reason we could
inquire about everything in detail. This factory is divided into different
parts whose headquarters are a very large, rectangular, two-story build-
ing, where there are large engines, and by means of them hundreds of
machines run. Our guide first took us on a tour of the upper level. First he
took us into a large room. There, several esteemed officers seated around
a long table were preparing the plan of a ship. When the diagram is pre-
pared, it is sent into another office, where a small model of the ship is
prepared in accordance with the diagram. This model is made of wood,
and despite being small, it is a complete image of the ship. This model is
first presented to the sulṭān for consideration, and, after approval, a ship
is prepared in accordance with its example. How could I have understood
the subtleties and finer points of these replica ships? But in appearance, it
seemed to be work of extreme precision and mastery. [97]
Torpedo Ships. Having seen these things, we went down below. Here,
hundreds of machines were running, and different jobs were being done.
On one side, parts were being cast. On another side, a hammer weighing
hundreds of maunds repeatedly fell onto many thick iron bars and turned
them into sheets. Ahead of this building there is a very large, long enclo-
sure. There, was a nearly complete ship there. All that remained was to
clad the sheet. Here, I saw many torpedo boats that had been prepared in
this very factory and had been launched into the ocean. There is nothing
in the upper level of these ships. The entire ship looks like a large wooden
board. The instruments of war and necessary things of every kind, that is,
the kitchen, sleeping chamber, dining room, in short, whatever there is, is
inside. Our guide even took us on a tour of one boat. But because there is
very little room inside, we began to suffocate in just a short while and soon
came outside. The extremely praiseworthy thing is that only Turks run
such a magnificent factory. All the officers, artisans, and employees are
Turks. Only a single European is an employee of ordinary rank, and even
he has been retained with regard to seniority.107 The engines, too, are pre-
pared here, and the Turks state that they are no less than the engines built
in Europe in any respect. One officer told me, “We have no dependency on
Europe in any tasks of this kind.”

Constantinople 91
The Slain of the Yang Charīs. In the history of the Turks, the word Yang
Charī [Janissary] is an extremely important word. [98] Sulṭān Ārkhān
[Orhan], who was the second among the Sulṭāns of Turkey to sit on the
throne, gave the order in 763 Hijrī [1361–62] that a particular number of
the prisoners of war who arrived as captives in large numbers each year
should be selected, and an army prepared from them. Ḥajī Baktāsh, who
was the spiritual mentor of the sulṭān, named the army the Yang Charī,
the meaning of which in the Turkish language is “new army.” Consider-
able increases were made in the size of this army because of the large
number of conquests. So much so that after two or three generations, the
army became the hand and arm of the government. It is a strange thing
that although these captives of war were generally Christian by descent,
and even after entering the army stood firm in their old religion, they
still had such genuine love for the Turkish government that the Turks
themselves could not have had more. It was by virtue of these daring, self-
sacrificing men that the Turks were able to make Europe their hunting
ground for some time. In 1826, when Sulṭān Maḥmūd sought to organize
the army on European principles, these people rebelled. The sulṭān had
already prepared a modern army. The people of the city, too, stood by the
royal modern army. In short, there was a harsh battle in Constantinople
itself. The Yang Charī army was completely destroyed. In addition, the
royal army, too, suffered a severe loss, and the Grand Wazīr and Shaikh
al-Islām were killed.108
This space is an edifying monument to this battle. There are full-length
statues of the Grand Wazīr, Shaikh al-Islām, and all the major, renowned
officers of the Yangcharī army. The formidable form of the soldiers and
generals, the garments and military weaponry of classical times, the scene
of silence and tranquility—by all these things gathered together, such an
awesome scene has been produced that one is afraid to go there even in
the daytime. [99] I saw two warriors sunk from head to toe in iron, helmet
on head, visor on face, iron gloves on hands, coat of mail and chār-ā’īnah
armor on body, iron boots up to the knees. In sum, no part of the body
was visible except for the eyes. By inquiry I learned that they are Kurdish
youths who were appointed especially to the service of his majesty. In my
estimation, there was no less than a burden of one maund of iron on their

92 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
body. It is a wonder how they fought with such weight. The garments of
officers are of a strange and wondrous kind. The turbans of some are a full
forearm’s length high each. There is an official guard at all times, and no
person can go there without obtaining a ticket.
Museum. Mūzah-khānah. Meaning museum. The museums are two. One
official, where there are extremely ancient stones and inscriptions, and
monumental things of this kind. There is even a stone coffin of Alexander
the Greek. Alas, I did not have a chance to visit it.
Some Christian businessman established the other. The building and
all the other objects are ordinary. All that is worth seeing are the statues
of people from different parts of the world. These statues have been made
so well that they seem completely real. I saw a woman whose lips were
extremely fat, and a pointed wooden peg had been pierced all the way
through her bottom lip. I learned that it is an ornament in that place. At
first I was extremely astonished. Then I thought that if in our country they
pierce noses and ears and have people wear nose rings and earrings, then
what fault did lips commit that they should be deprived of such adorn-
ment? [100]
A Painful Spectacle. Here, I saw a strange, painful spectacle, the effect of
which remained on my heart for a while. In a separate room, there are sev-
eral women who are afflicted with various kinds of torture. One is being
pressed in a torture rack. On the back of another, they have set a burning
slip of metal so that from the neck to the waist, four fingers’ length of skin
has peeled off. The others are similarly being tortured in a strange way.
From their appearance and style of dress, these women seem wealthy and
noble. Most are young, attractive, and of delicate figure. I was severely
astonished to think which tyrannical hands had been so audacious as to
raise a hand against these goddesses of beauty!! By inquiry, I learned that
when the Islamic government was destroyed in Spain, and the sultanate
of the Christians was established, Muslims were generally compelled to
change their religion, and because the trace of Islam could not easily be
erased from their hearts, they were tortured in various ways and manners,
and, on account of their helplessness and weakness, even more tyranny

Constantinople 93
was enacted upon women. These tyrannized women are memorials of
this admonitory and morally instructive event. At that time I thought,
“Aha! It is these very Christians who deride us that Islam was spread by
the sword!!!”
I could not figure out to what end the founder of the museum, who is
a Christian, has kept these images here. Does he desire to show this proud
achievement of the Christians? And since the government of the Turks
does not object and intervene, does it desire to offer proof of its impar-
tiality? I extremely dislike and disapprove of the idea that the unpleasant
events that have taken place at some time among different nations of the
world should be brought once more into public view. [101]
Sights
In Constantinople and its outlying area and vicinity, wondrous, pleasant
natural sights are in abundance, and it is a blessing that the people of the
city appreciate the value of this boon. A particular day is fixed for each
sight. On that day, there is a wondrous, pleasant gathering there. Alas, the
people of our region are not aware of a taste for natural scenery. Otherwise,
people would have travelled to Constantinople specifically to see these
sights and to enjoy them, and this would not have been considered strange.
I visited two or three of them, and I shall write brief accounts of them.
Khūnkar Ṣūī. Khūnkar Ṣūī [Hünkar Suyu] is the most pleasant and
enchanting of all the sights in Constantinople. On this basis, it has been
associated with the name of the Great Sulṭān. Khūnkar is an alteration
of the Persian word khūngar. In Turkish, they call the Emperor khūn
kā mālik [the lord of blood] or khūn-rez [blood-spiller] and the mean-
ings of sū’ī are water and spring.109 On this basis, the literal translation of
Khūngar Ṣūī is “royal spring.” This place is located at a distance of twenty
to twenty-five miles from the city. A range of mountains stretches far into
the distance, and it is extremely lush and verdant. In it, one area, which is
located on the upper surface of the mountain, appears extremely attrac-
tive. The place where the spectators gather in particular is extremely pleas-
ant. There are lines of shady trees on both sides. As far as the eye can see,

94 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
one sees nothing but verdure. There is a waterfall on one side whose water
gathers in a pool. All around, beneath the trees, there are parties of two to
four people each. A round of tea and coffee is served. Music is played at the
pool, [102] and there is French and Turkish singing. Jesters put on shows.
Five or six steps above is the actual summit of the mountain, and it
is extremely open, level, and shady. This place is reserved for women to
sit, and many Turkish ladies are always gathered. Covering a distance of
twenty or thirty miles, climbing the mountain, and riding a horse or mule
is a matter of no little discomfort for delicate-figured women, but this
place is so alluring that all discomforts can be endured for it.
Maqrī Kūī [Makrıköy].110 This is a coffeehouse that is exactly on the edge
of the sea and is a place of extremely pleasant ambiance. Waves repeatedly
come and crash against the steep banks, and one feels a wondrous sense of
joy. One special thing about this place is that six or seven Jewish women sit
on a high platform and sing Arabic songs. Because I had never heard Ara-
bic music before, it left a special impression on me. Everyone sang together
as they played a kind of frame drum.
Muḥarram
The Muḥarram of this place is also something worth mentioning.111 The
number of people of ‘Ajam, who reside here by reason of different connec-
tions, is no less than fifty or sixty thousand.112 A great many are employ-
ees in government offices. Many are traders, professionals, and laborers.
Although these people are spread throughout all parts of the city, where
they live in abundance is a neighborhood by the name of Wālidah Khānah
[Valide Hanı].113 At Muharram time, assemblies of great pomp and parade,
and the massive gathering of lamentation and weeping, mostly take place
right here. [103] In the assemblies here, there is no tradition of soz and taḥt
al-lafẓ; only narration takes place.114 And in truth this alone is the purpose
of the assembly of mourning. The general practice of this place is that,
first, a person, standing near the minbar, recites poems related to the vir-
tues and accomplishments of Janāb-i Amīr (‘a) and Imām Ḥusain, peace
be upon him.115 Then a learned scholar sits on the minbar and describes

Constantinople 95
the circumstances of Karbala extremely finely and clearly in the form of
a sermon. I was very happy at the fact that Turks generally participate in
these assemblies with decorum and sincerity. So much so that the sermon
that takes place, except for one or two occasions, in all other assemblies,
takes place in Turkish in consideration of the Turks.116
The Strange and Wondrous Methods of Mourning. There are a few
methods of mourning, and some are extremely wondrous and impressive.
The mourning of the lowest order is that they beat the chest with extreme
force, so much so that the flesh there swells up. The second method is to
mourn with chains. There is a circle of thirty to forty people, and they beat
chains on their chest or back with such force that the sound carries some
distance. The third method is to mourn with swords, and this is exclusive
to the shab-i shahādat.
117 The mourners, standing in ranks holding bare
swords in their hands, repeat “Yā Ḥusain!” in a complete state of won-
drous passion and rapture as they go on striking themselves with swords
on their heads, foreheads, and shoulders. Sprays of blood fly up from the
wounds and fall upon and cover the entire body, and it is as if the circle of
mourning turns into a field of battle. There is an extremely dense crowd of
people to see this edifying and admonishing spectacle, and it is difficult to
reach there.118 [104]
Salāmlaq or Sulṭān’s Guard and Eid al-Z ¨
uḥā
There is nothing more impressive or interesting in Constantinople than
the Salāmlaq. Salāmlaq is a Turkish word whose literal translation is “to
make salaam.” Because on this occasion the army and the army com-
manders come to make salaam to the sulṭān, they designate this ceremony
Salāmlaq. The sulṭān generally never leaves the royal palace. He only
graces the congregational masjid to read Friday namāz, and that is where,
after prayers, this ceremony is performed. The reality is that it is difficult,
severely difficult, to draw a picture of the grandeur and magnificence that
appears at that time by means of language or pen. Despite the fact that
this occasion takes place four times in a month and forty-eight times in a
year, and for this reason it can be considered an ordinary thing, there is

96 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
always such a crowd of spectators that people climb into trees and onto
men’s shoulders to watch the spectacle. European dignitaries and travelers
who come to tour Constantinople never let this occasion slip from their
hand. There is a gallery above the thoroughfare of the royal guard. Having
bought tickets, esteemed people are given permission to sit there. Thus, a
sizable assembly of these esteemed spectators is found every Friday. Dur-
ing my stay, many chief members of the sultanate of Hungary had come to
tour Constantinople and had joined this assembly. [105]
I had already heard of these states of affairs in Hindustan. For this
reason, immediately upon arriving at Constantinople, I made plans to see
it. I took along a Syrian Arab, whom I had recently met, and reached the
Ḥamīdiyah Congregational Mosque [Hamidiye Camii]. Having reached
there, I looked to find that ranks of soldiers had formed stretching far off
into the distance, and it was difficult for the eye to reach the royal guard. I
had no choice but to turn back. Ḥusain Ḥasīb Āfandī was once the Turk-
ish Consul at Bombay and now is police commissioner in Constantino-
ple. He knew me by means of the fact that in the Russian War, I had sent
three thousand rupees through him to Constantinople as the secretary of
a society.119 On the basis of this means of introduction, I appeared in his
service. He treated me with extreme kindness and said, “Come on Friday
to the Ḥamīdiyah Congregational Mosque. I shall hold a ticket for you.”
But unfortunately (and, if you ask the truth, then, fortunately), when I
arrived there, he was nowhere to be found. I waited for him at the door of
the masjid for a while. At nearly one o’clock, when the roar of the sulṭān’s
approach began, the armies, spreading far into the distance, formed ranks
in the shape of a crescent, and all the roads stopped. Disappointed, I
entered the masjid and regretted that this Friday, too, had been a miss. A
little while had passed when there came a sound like that of thunder, and
the entire area erupted with echoing roars. I learned that the sulṭān’s cav-
alcade had drawn near, and the cry was “Pādshāhim choq yashā,”* which
is the national cry of the Turks. These cries were raised three times in
*
The literal translation of this is, “May our emperor live long.”

Constantinople 97
succession. The sulṭān’s guard arrived at the masjid, and the roar of the
cries had not yet quieted when the muezzin, who was waiting for the beau-
tiful appearance of the sulṭān, raised the cry of Allāhu akbar. Both sounds
mixed together left a wondrous impression on the heart. The sulṭān was
riding in an open carriage. Because the courtyard of the masjid is not a
part of the masjid, meaning they do not perform namāz there and they
can go there wearing shoes, the carriage entered the courtyard and came
to a stop near the door. [106] The masjid is two stories, and on the upper
story is a gallery, which is the place reserved exclusively for the sulṭān’s
namāz. Having stepped down from the carriage, the sulṭān went to the
upper story and, as he went inside, satin curtains were released over the
windows to the gallery so that no one could see him.
When people were calmly seated, the preacher began the sermon.
Regrettably, the preacher was a Turk. He was not an Arab. Thus, there
was not that quality and effect in his tone and accent which is exclusive
to the Arab. Still, when the second sermon began, and when he, gestur-
ing toward the sulṭān, recited the following words in a passionate voice,
“ Allāhuma unṣur hāżā al-sulṭān al-suḷtān ibn al-sulṭān al-khāqān ibn
al-khāqān al-sulṭān ‘Abd al-Ḥamīd Khān,”120 it produced a strange, won-
drous feeling. My state was such that tears continuously flowed from my
eyes, and for a while prayerful words poured from my lips. At exactly
that moment, fifteen or twenty people stood up at once in whose hands
were petitions and appeals. These people raised their hands in the sulṭān’s
direction and offered prayers for him as they presented their petitions.
The petition officer collected and submitted their papers. I saw several as
they, gesturing toward the sulṭān, bowed to the ground and, touching the
ground with their hand, kissed the hand. Although all these matters went
against the custom and tranquility of the sermon, they did not lack their
own an appealing quality. I learned by inquiry that people for whom it
is otherwise impossible to access the Great Sulṭān express their concerns
in this way, [107] and because the temperament of the sulṭān is naturally
beneficent and generous, the custom is not stopped.
After namāz, Ḥusain Ḥasīb Āfandī happened to run into me and com-
plained, “I was looking all over for you. Where did you disappear to? You

98 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
will not get a ticket for the upper gallery now, but I will find an even better
opportunity for you.” Having performed namāz, when all the people went
outside, the sulṭān came down from the gallery and stopped on a stair-
way wherefrom the Salāmlaq could be seen well, and no one could see the
sulṭān. The army officers and the pāshās, having formed a line, stood on
the right side of the courtyard. Ḥusain Ḥasīb brought me to stand in the
line and told the people, “He is our guest.” An esteemed officer (because of
fine moral character) stepped back and cleared a space for me.
The Arrival of the Troops. After a little while, the troops began to arrive.
From the royal palace to the masjid, there is a wide and sloping road. The
troops stood in ranks in the form of a crescent stretching far into the dis-
tance. Passing by the front of the royal palace, they entered the main gate
of the masjid and left by the other gate. The orderliness of the ranks, the
different divisions of cavalry, foot soldiers, naval, ground troops, artil-
lery, riflemen, Turks, Kurds, and Arabs, the elegant and regimented pace,
splendid glittering weapons, uniforms of different and attractive styles,
the coming of armies in succession and passing in front of their emperor
with loyal passion; it was a strange and wondrous scene that can in no
way be described. [108] There were turbans on the heads of the Arab regi-
ment, which is the imperial guard, and the green ends of their turbans,
flying in the breeze, exhibited a wondrous pleasure. For three continuous
hours this military sea continued to billow, and about ten thousand troops
passed by. In the end, both of the sulṭān’s princes came, and came with
wondrous glory. They were in military dress, and swords were bound at
their waists. Although they were around ten or twelve years old, the man-
ner in which they rode on horseback and the boldness and glory that was
expressed by their faces cannot be put into words. When the princes, too,
had gone, the sulṭān came down the stairs, and the ranks of army officers
and pāshās, which included me, too, immediately bowed for salaam. I was
rapt with wonder from the beginning, and my eyes were fixed in a gaze.
It had always been my intention that if I had occasion to have an audience
with the sulṭān, I would pay my respects with extreme supplication, but
I was in such a state of rapture that the entire rank remained bowed for
a while and I, eyes fixed in a gaze, stood there just as before. Of course,

Constantinople 99
prayerful words flowed from my tongue and not intentionally, either;
rather, I had lost all control.
Having taken five or six steps on foot, the sulṭān mounted his carriage.
The officers made salaam once again, and the strange and wondrous scene
suddenly became hidden from the eyes: dīdah-i man bāz o ba-khwābam
hanūz.
121 At the moment when the sulṭān, having come down from the
staircase, moved toward the carriage, there was a distance of only three or
four arm’s lengths from our rank to him, and for this reason I could see
him very well. The appearance of the sulṭān is as follows: of medium stat-
ure, rather, a bit taller; lean body; oblong face; dignity and intentness drip
from his appearance—rather, it seems that he is thinking about some-
thing. [109] Completely simple clothing, that is, a coat of black broadcloth
and an ordinary Turkish cap.
The Practice of Salāmlaq. The practice of Salāmlaq has existed for some
time among the Turks and has become a part of the ceremonies of the
sultanate. Royal majesty and magnificence alone are not intended by it.
Rather, a great benefit is that a large part of the army is checked each week,
and in this way all the troops that reside in the capital and its environs
pass through the inspection of the sulṭān several times each year. The
Sulṭān of the Age can make a sufficient estimate of the state of the army,
and thoughts of passion and loyalty to the emperor become refreshed in
the hearts of the army.
When I returned to my residence having seen this spectacle, my heart
was filled with passion and effect. By the incitement of poetic emotions, a
few lines spontaneously came and went across my tongue. Taking up pen
and paper, I sat down and penned a few couplets. Then the idea occurred
to me that there would be even more material on the day of Eid. When I
had seen that, too, I should write. Thus, all the couplets of the introduction
that had been composed at that time, I wrote down and set aside. By these
couplets at the end of the introduction:
And this you ask—that from that place of beautiful sites,
What have your eyes obtained?
to this couplet:

100 Turkey, Egypt, and Syria
Because the gathering is full of beautiful visions,
The garment hem of my eye is filled with spectacle.122
this impressive and passionate scene is meant. [110]
Eid Procession. There was no Salāmlaq on the day of Eid, and for this
reason the number of troops was low, but the glory and grandeur, maj-
esty and magnificence, passion and effect, were a bit greater than even
the Salāmlaq. The troops began to arrive at around eight o’clock and the
unbroken series continued for an hour to an hour and a half. After that, a
great number of empty carriages came. People wondered, “What is meant
by them?” Then all at once, ranks of foot soldiers appeared in the distance.
It became known that all the wazīrs, pāshās, army officers, and major
regional officers were coming on foot in the sulṭān’s procession. These
ranks continued for half a mile on both sides of the street, and a strange
and wondrous glory and grandeur was expressed by their fashion and
dress. Golden flowers [epaulets] on their shoulders; writing in gold and
silver thread on their garment hems and sleeves; chests covered in bejew-
eled and golden medals; the reflection of the sun on all this; the entire field
sparkled. When this rank had gone, then the world-adorning beauty of
the sulṭān appeared. The lauded gentleman was mounted on horseback.
His dress was entirely simple. A few great, renowned military officers were
in stirrups to accompany him. The horse slowly and gently raised its step,
and at each step the cry “Bādshāhim choq yashā” was raised such that the
entire area echoed with thunderous roars.
When I returned after seeing this scene, I sat down with ink and pen
so that I could show others what I had seen myself. But alas, extreme
alas, the pen fell entirely short. The image that I have drawn is an entirely
incomplete image. [111]
Eid Mas˙nawī123
June 1892124
Location: Constantinople
O happy messenger of mine, yes, come!
Allah has furnished you with a good end.125



</book>